<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The logike of the moste excellent philosopher P. Ramus martyr, newly translated, and in diuers places corrected, after the mynde of the author. Per M. Roll. Makylmenæum Scotum, rogatu viri honestissimi, M. Ægidii Hamlini</title>
            <title>Dialectica. English</title>
            <author>Ramus, Petrus, 1515-1572.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1574</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 129 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05111</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15246</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107927</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843619</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843619</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8364</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05111)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8364)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 712:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The logike of the moste excellent philosopher P. Ramus martyr, newly translated, and in diuers places corrected, after the mynde of the author. Per M. Roll. Makylmenæum Scotum, rogatu viri honestissimi, M. Ægidii Hamlini</title>
                  <title>Dialectica. English</title>
                  <author>Ramus, Petrus, 1515-1572.</author>
                  <author>MacIlmaine, Rollo.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 101, [1] p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Vautroullier dwelling in the Blackefrieres,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno M. D. Lxxiiii [1574] Cum Privilegio.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Ramus, Petrus.  Dialectica.</note>
                  <note>Woodcut portrait of Ramus bound before title page.</note>
                  <note>Page 82 misnumbered 52.</note>
                  <note>Errata on recto of G3, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Logic --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:8364:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Petrus Ramus or Pierre de la
Ramée</figDesc>
                  <head>PETRVS R. M. S. AET LVII</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8364:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LOGIKE OF THE MOSTE EXCELLENT PHILO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher P. Ramus Martyr,
Newly tranſlated, and in diuers places corrected, after the mynde of the
Author.</p>
            <p>PER M. Roll. Makylmenaeum Scotum, rogatu viri ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtiſſimi,
M. Aegidij Hamlini.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <q>ANCHORA SPEI</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London by Thomas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troullier dwelling in the
Blackefrieres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ANNO M.D.LXXIIII.</p>
            <p>CVM PRIVILEGIO.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:8364:2"/>
            <l>The lyuelie pithe of Platoes witte and Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtots ingeine,</l>
            <l>The pleaſaunte vayne of Cicero, and of Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiliane</l>
            <l>The iudgment highe, here thou maieſt ſee: therfor if thou be
wiſe,</l>
            <l>No farther ſeeke but in this booke thy ſelf doe
exerciſe.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:8364:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WORSHYPFVLL M. ROBERT WYKES OF Dodyngton in the Countye
of Glouceter Eſquyer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lexander Kynge of Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done (moſt Worſhipfull Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caenas) not
ſo muche for his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyaunt and martiall factes (althoughe they were moſt
vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious) as for his great loue and ardente zeale whiche he bare to vertue
and knowledge, hathe bene of all men hade in moſte worthie estimation and
goodlye memorye. Iob called the ſeruaunte of God, althoughe he was wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie
to be prayſed of all men for his iustice and equitye, yet he was moste
commended for his ſyngular patyence in tyme of tribulation and great
calamytie. But when I conſidere with my ſelf your inſatiable deſyre and
moste fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent loue, not onlye in the followynge of your owne ſtudie, but
alſo in the promouinge and furtherynge of others: your greate patience and
incredible constance, in ſufferynge affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and abydyng aequitie: I am
compelled to confeſſe that there is none neyther amongeſt the prophane
and ethnycke authours, neyther amongeſt theccleſyasticall and ſpyrytuall
fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <pb n="4" facs="tcp:8364:3"/> (of what estate or qualitie ſo euer they were)
with the whiche ye may not be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, yea or rather preferred. For yf
Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der were prayſed that in the myddeſt of his triumphant victories he
dyd beare abrode with hym Ilyas the famous worke of homer containinge the
battayles and destruction of Troye: How muche more are ye to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended that
in the myddeſt of your calamitie doe bothe nyght and day where ſoeuer ye
be, carie and reade a more worthie and pretious worke? Alexander in
proſperitie tooke plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to reade Homere treactinge, of martiall factes,
to thende he mought guyde his armye accordinge to the exacte rule therin
decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: ye take pleaſure in aduerſitie to reade the holye Scrypture and
worde of God, to thende ye may gouerne your lyfe accordyng to the wyll and
commaundemente of God. Where Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xander was, there was prophane Homere: w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here
ye are there is the holye Byble. When A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander did ſleape Homere was his
boulster: when ye doe ſleape, the Byble is your pyllowe Alexander for all hys
ryches is prayſed for the continuall reading of one booke: what ſhall I
then ſaye of you that haue bestowed no lyttle parte of your goodes in buiynge
of moſt <pb n="5" facs="tcp:8364:3"/> worthie workes. Iob whiche is ſet before our
eyes thexample of a ſyngular patience beinge extreamly afflicted in outward
thynges, and in hys bodye, throughe his great tormentes and afflictyons brasted
forthe into many incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenyences both of wordes and ſentences, and ſhewed
hym ſelf as a deſperate man in many thynges, and as one that woulde
reſyſt God, Ye hauynge no leſſe occaſion to complayne beinge moste
vniustly ſpoyled of your goods troubled in mynde and conſcience, threatned
dayly by your ennemyes doe notwithstandin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge constantly reſyste acknowledgyng
God to haue ſecret iudgments, to chastyſe thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlye whome he
loueth, and to lette the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate runne to destruction. Theſe and other
your moste ſingular vertues hauinge conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and experimented the good
will and mynd which you beare to the furtheraunce and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng forthe of all
ſciences, I coulde fynde none more apte, or worthie vnder whoſe name this
golden treaſure ſhoulde come abrode, then his whoſe vertue and good
behauiour, mighte geue ſome place and authoritie to the ſame. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
therebe many more adorned with ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and poſſeſſions of this worlde
yet in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge forthe of vertue and ſinguler patience I <pb n="6" facs="tcp:8364:4"/> fynde none at all. Nowe therfore to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude (Sythens, I knowe you to
be moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienated from all ambition) I beſeeche you to receyue, this my
ſmall preſente in good part, hauing rather reſpecte to the mynde of the
giuer then to the gyfte it ſelf, althoughe moſt pretious. So I committe you
to the protection of God almyghtie wiſhynge his heauenly Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, that ye
may constantlie perſeuere as ye haue begonne, bothe in your ſpirituall and
temporall affaires, to thende that ye liuing godlie in this worlde maye obtayne
that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Crowne of glorie whiche our Sauiour Ieſus Christe hathe
prepared to all thoſe that doe patiently: watche for his appearynge to whome
withe the father and the holy Ghoſt be all laude, honour &amp; prayſe
worlde without ende.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:8364:4"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER CONTAINING the occaſion of the
ſetting forthe of this booke, the vtilitie and profitte of the ſame, the
vſe and facilitie, vvith the declaration of thre golden documents or rules
appartaining to the matter of euery arte, and laſt a brief declaration of the
methode and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to be obſerued in all artes and ſciences.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>EING it is the dewtye of all Chriſtians (beloued Reader) to
la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by all meanes, that they maye profytte and ayde their bretherne, and to
hyde or kepe ſecrete no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, whiche they knowe maye bring greate vtilitie
to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealthe: I thought it my dewtie (hauing perceyued the greate
commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie whiche this booke bryngethe to the Reader of what ſtate and
qualitie ſoeuer he be) to make thee and all others to whoſe knowledge it
ſhall come per takers thereof. But leaſt thou thynke that thy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and
payne ſhoulde be loſt in reading of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, ſeyng ſo many bookes
goyng abrode vnder glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious names, hauing in deade lytle or no vtilitie, but
wrapped al together with innumerable difficulties: I ſhall in fewe wordes
ſhewe the, the matter contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this booke, the methode and forme of the
ſame, howe eaſye it is aboue all others to be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, howe thou
ſhalt applye it to all artes and ſciences, and ſhortlie that no arte or
ſcience maye eyther be taught or learned perfectlie without the knowledge of
the ſame. As fore the matter whiche it containethe, thou ſhalt vnderſtand
that there is nothing appartayning to dialectike eyther in Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotles xvij.
booke of logike, in his eight bookes of Phiſike, or in his xiiij. bookes of
Philoſophie, in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero his bookes of Oratorie, or in Quintilian (in the 
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8364:5"/> which there is almoſt nothing that dothe not ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
appartayne to the inuention of argumentes a diſpoſition of the ſame, but
thou ſhalt fynde it ſhortlie and after a perfecte methode in this booke
declared. For thou ſhalt fynde no argument which is not eyther referred to
one of the nyne argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes artificial, or to the vnartificiall: no ſort of
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition whiche dothe not appartayne eyther to the iudgement of the
propoſition, ſylogiſme or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode. But thou wylt ſaye howe is it
poſſible that this lytle booke is able to containe all that, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the
forenamed bookes (beyng ſo manie) do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the entreate? In deede thou haſt no
lytle occaſion to maruell, but (hauing more deapely conſidered the matter)
I beleue thou ſhall not maruell ſo mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. For in this booke there is thre
documents or ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les kept, whiche in deede ought to be obſerued in all artes
and ſciences. The firſt is, that in ſetting forthe of an arte we gather
only togeather that which dothe appartayne to the Arte whiche we intreate of,
leau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to all other Artes that which is proper to them, this rule (which maye
be called the rule of Iuſtice) thou ſhalt ſee here well obſerued. For
here is all w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hich dothe appartayne to logike, and nothing nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Grammer,
Rethorike, Phiſicke, nor any other arte. This is that documente which Apelles
many yeares agoe dyd ſignifie to vs, for when as the Shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker reprehended
the ſhoo of Apelles image, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles tooke it in good parte, becauſe it dyd
apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to the Shoomakers arte: but when paſſing his boundes he began
to fynde faulte whith the clothes alſo, Apelles ſayde to hym, <hi>Nihil
Sutor vltra crepidam,</hi> which ſignifie the that the Shoomaker ſhoulde
kepe hym with in the boundes of his arte. And therfore <pb n="9" facs="tcp:8364:5"/>
(beloued Reader) all thoſe which eyther write or teache either diuinitie,
Phiſicke, the lawe or any other thing do violate and breake this documente,
when they degreſſe from their purpoſe and do rayle vpon other thinges
nothing partayning therto. For howſoeuer they write or teache (ſo it be
from their purpoſe) it is to be had of no eſtimation. Is he not worthie to
be mocked of all men, that purpoſe the to wryte of Grammer, and in euery
other chapiter mynglethe ſomthing of Logicke, and ſome thing of Rethoricke:
and contrarie when he purpoſe the to write of Logicke dothe ſpeake of
Grammer and of Rethoricke? that takethe a text to preache of faſting and
diſputethe the moſt parte of his howre of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges or ſwearing? that
promyſethe to ſhewe me the cauſes and ſignes of the ſtone, and
tellethe me many tales pertainning to the gowte? that when he is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of
contractes or obligations, aunſwerethe of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie or bondage? Or if the
Aſtrologian being asked of the eclips of the ſonne, ſhoulde aunſwere me
ſome thing concerning the motion of the ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res? And yet we ſee the
moſt parte of our learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bothe in their teaching and writing (to the
greate hurte and domage of youthe) moſt vnſhamfullie do vſe the ſame
which I would to god were amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. The ſeconde document (which diligently is
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in this booke) is that all the rules and prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptes of thine arte
be of neceſſitie tru, whiche A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle requirethe in the ſeconde booke
of his Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litikes and in diuerſe chapiters in his former booke. Thou ſhalt
violate this document, whenſoeuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt thy precepts in writing or
teaching, thou ſhalt myngle any falſe, ambiguous, or vncerteine thing: as
if in theaching me my logicke, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtethe <pb n="10" facs="tcp:8364:6"/> in
rules to inuente argumentes, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pone and iudge the ſame, thou
ſhouldeſt begyn to tell me ſome trickes of poyſonable ſophiſtrie:
and when thou ſhouldeſt teache me the worde of God truly, thou goeſt
aboute to deceaue me by tellyng me mans inuentions: and if thou ſhouldeſt
(being deſtitute of good arguments to proue thy matter) be lie ſome
aunciant writer to beguyle the rude and ignorant people, or forge ſome
Authors to colour thy knauerie which neuer was, or wrote at any time. I doubte
not (gentle Reader) but thou haſt read of ſuche felowes: alwayes call thou
vpon god that it wyll pleaſe his heauenlie Maieſtie to plante this our rule
of veritie in the hartes of all men, but moſt chieflie in the breaſtes of
the Paſtors of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, who haue the charge and diſpenſation of his
holye worde. The third documente which thou ſhalt note herein obſerued, is,
that thou intreate of thy rules which be generall generallye, and thoſe
whiche be ſpeciall ſpeciallie, and at one tyme, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any vaine
repetitions, which dothe nothing but fyll vp the paper. For it is not
ſufficient that thou kepe the rule of veritie and iuſtice, without thou
obſerue alſo this documente of wiſedome, to diſpute of euery thing
according to his nature. Doe not entreate therfore generall matters
particulerly, nor particuler matters generally, for in ſo doing thou
playeſt the Sophiſtes parte, as Ariſtotle tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chethe in the firſt booke
of his poſteriors, and ſhalt be compelled to vſe tautalogies and vaine
repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions whiche thow knoweſt to be moſt pernicious to all artes and
ſciences. For if I aske thee what is Lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gicke? and thou aunſwereſt, that
which teachethe to inuente argumentes, thou aunſwereſt trulye but 
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8364:6"/> not wyſelie, becauſe thou intreareſt a generall thing
particulerlie: I aske the for the definition of the w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hole arte, and thow
geueſt me the definition of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, which is but a parte of the arte. And
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, if I aske the what is inuention, and thou aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereſt an arte
whiche teachethe to diſpute well, ſurely thou aunſwereſt not wyſelie,
for thou intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt a particuler thing generallie: I aske of thee, the
definition of a parte of the arte, and thou geueſt me the definition of the
whole arte. Note well theſe thre rules in reading of thyne Authors: ſee, if
they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntangle them ſelues,
with thinges nothing appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eining to their purpoſe: yf they trouble thee with
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mbiguous or deceiptfull
ſpeakings, and do not handle euery thing after his nature. Take the
forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed bookes, and with
thy rule of iuſtice geue to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uery arte his owne, and
ſurely if my iudgement do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne not farre deceaue me, thou muſt geue ſome
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing to the arte of Grammer,
ſome thing to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oricke,
ſome thing to the fower mathematicall
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtes, Arithemeticke,
Geometrie, Aſtrologie and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſicke,
ſome thing alſo (althoughe but litle) to Phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cke, naturall Philoſophie, and diuinitie. And
yet all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at is in theſe
bookes (only the fore ſaid digreſſions
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cepted) dothe appartaine
eyther to the inuention <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f
Logicke, or els to the iudgemente. Now gather
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>geather that wich
remainethe, after euery arte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
the receiued his owne, and ſee if there be any falſe,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mbiguous or vncertein thing
amongeſt it, and yf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here
be (as in dede there is ſome) take thy docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ente of veritie, and put out all ſuche
ſophiſticall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eakinges.
And laſt perceiue if all thinges be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d according to their nature, the generall
gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lye, and the
particuler particulerlie, if not, take <pb n="12" facs="tcp:8364:7"/> thy rule of
wyſdome, and do according as the third documente teachethe thee: abolyſhe
all tautalogies and vayne repetitions, and ſo thus muche being do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, thou
ſhalt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehende the reſt into a litle rome. And this muche concerning the
matter intreated in this booke. The forme and methode which is kept in this
arte, comaundethe that the thing which is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely moſt cleare, be
firſt placed: and ſecondly that which is next cleare, &amp; ſo forthe
whith the reſt. And therfore it continually procedethe from the generall to
the ſpeciall and ſinguler. The definition as moſt generall is firſt
placed, next folowethe the diuiſion, firſt into the partes, and next into
the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and kyndes. Euery parte and forme is defined in his owne place, and
made manifeſt by examples of auncient Authors, and laſt the members are
limited and ioined togeather with ſhort tranſitions for the recreation of
the Reader. This is that only perfecte methode which Plato and Ariſtotle dyd
knowe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued by many noble wryters, bothe Hiſtoriogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, Orators,
and Poetes, and now laſt (beyng ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by ignoraunce many yeres)
rayſed as it were from deathe, by the moſt learned and Martyr to God,
<hi>Petrus Ramus,</hi> who hathe not only proued with ſtronge argumentes, but
in very deede ſet before our eyes that this perfecte methode maye be
accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date to all artes &amp; ſciences. What ſhall we ſaye then of
thoſe, that in teaching and writing (to the greate hurte of the memorie)
dothe put as it were the tayle formeſt, hauing no regard how euerie thinge is
placed, but euen as it chaunſethe to come into their Mouthes, ſo lettethe
it go. Dyd euer Plato or Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle ſo? no in deede. But that thou mayeſt
a lytle the better perceyue the vtilitie of this arte, and howe 
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8364:7"/> farre the vſe of it dothe extende, I wyll ſhortly
ſhewe thee howe thou ſhalt accommodate the ſame to all artes and
ſciences, ſetting before thyne eyes one or two for an example. And firſt
what arte ſo euer thou purpoſeſt to intreate of, thou muſt come
garnyſhed with thieſe thre, Iuſtice, Veritie, &amp; Wyſdome, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
is ſayde: and then if thou be a deuine this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode willethe thee that in
place of the definition, thou ſett forthe ſhortly the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of the text,
whiche thou haſt taken in hand to interprete: next to parte thy text into a
fewe heads that the auditor may the better retaine thy ſayinges: Thirdly to
intreate of euery heade in his owne place with the ten places of inuention,
ſhewing them the cauſesi, theffectes, the adioints and circunſtances: to
bring in thy compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons with the reſt of artificiall places: and laſt
to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke thy matter playne and manifeſt with familiar exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples &amp;
aucthorities out of the worde of God: to ſett before the auditor (as euery
heade ſhall geue the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion) the horrible and ſharpe punyſhing of
diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and the ioyfull promiſes appartayning to the obedient and
godlie. Yf thou be a Phiſition and willing to teache (as for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple) of a
feuer, this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode willethe thee to ſhewe firſt the definition, that is,
what a feuer is, next the deuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, declaring what ſor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of feuer it is,
whether the quartane, quotidian, hecticke, or what other: thirdly to come to
the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of inuention, and ſhewe fyrſt the cauſes of the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer euery
one in order, the efficient, as maye be hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te meates, the matter as
melancolie, choler, or ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me rotten humor, and ſo forthe with the formale
cauſes and finall. The ſeconde place is theffecte, ſhewe then what the
feuer is able to bring forthe, whether deathe or no. The third place wiſhethe
thee <pb n="14" facs="tcp:8364:8"/> to tell the ſubiecte of the feuer, whether it be in
the vaines, artiers, or els where. The fowrthe to ſhewe the ſignes and
tokens which appeare to pretende lyfe or deathe: and to be ſhorte, thou
ſhalt paſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughe the reſt of the artificiall places, and do that
which is requyred in euery of them: And laſt come to the confirmyng of thy
ſayinges by examples, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthorities, and (as Hippocrates &amp; Galen haue
done) by hiſtories and long experience. After this methode Heraclitus the
Philoſopher examyned the phiſitions whiche came to heale hym, and becauſe
they were ignorant and could not aunſwere to his interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he ſent
them away, and woulde receyue none of their Medicens: for (ſayd he) yf ye can
not ſhewe me the cauſes of my ſicknes, much leſſe are ye able to take
the cauſe awaye. So the lawyer ſhall pleade his cauſe, in prouyng or
diſprouyng after as his matter ſhall requier, with theſe ten places of
Inuention, &amp; diſpone euery thing orderlie into his propoſitions,
ſyllogiſmes, and methode. So ſhall the Orator de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clayme: the
Mathematician ſette forthe his demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations: and to be ſhorte bothe in
wrytyng, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, &amp; in learnyng, thou mayeſt alwayes kepe the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe thre
golden documentes in intreatyng thy matter, and this moſt ingenious and
artificiall methode for the exacte forme and diſpoſition of the ſame.
After the exacte obſeruation of the forſaid materiall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuments and
naturall methode thou haſt this lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le booke ſett furthe to the, whiche
beyng well peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is able to bring more profytt to the (I ſpeake af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
experience) then all thy fower yeares ſtudie in Plato or Ariſtotle as they
are now extant. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the greate vtilitie wiche thou ſhalt
apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of this booke, the facilitie and eaſynes of the ſame 
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8364:8"/> is not a litle to be commended. For heare thou haſt
nothing to learne (and yet thou ſhalt learne all) but onlye ten places of
inuention, with the diſpoſition of the propoſition, ſyllogiſme, and
methode. Euery place of inuention and euery ſort of diſpoſition is made
ſo clere and manyfeſt with examples choſen out of the moſt auncyent
Authors, that almoſt by thy ſelf (yf thou haue any quicknes of ſpirite)
thou mayeſt attayne in the ſpace of two monthes the perfecte knowledge of
the ſame. Heare I will ſpeake nothing of the enuious, that thinkethe it not
decent to wryte any liberall arte in the vulgar tongue, but woulde haue all
thinges kept cloſe eyther in the Hebrewe, Greke, or Latyn tongues. I knowe
what greate hurte hathe come to the Churche of God by the defence of this
miſcheuous opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yet I woulde aske them one thing that thou mayeſt knowe
their deceiptfull policie, and that their ſaying hathe no grounde of veritie.
Whether wrote Moyſes (the Hebrewe and deuyne) and after hym Eſdras in the
Hebrewe and vulgar tongue or in ſome other ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge tongue? Did
Ariſtotle and Plato Greke Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, Hipocrates and Galen Greke
Phiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, leaue the Greke tongue, becauſe it was their natiue lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,
to ſeke ſome Hebrewe or Latin? Did Cicero who was a Latiniſt borne write
his Philoſophie and Rethoricke in the Greke tongue, or was he content with
his mother tongue? and ſuerly as he teſtifiethe hym ſelf he had the
perfecte knowledge of the Greke tongue, yet he wrothe nothing therin wich we
haue extant at this daye. Shall we then thinke the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſhe or Engliſhe
tongue, it not fitt to wrote any arte into? no in dede. But peraduenture thou
wylt ſaye that there is not Scottyſhe wordes for to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare 
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8364:9"/> and expreſſe all thinges contayned into libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
artes, truthe it is: neither was there Latin wordes to expreſſe all thinges
writen in the Hebrewe and Greke tongues: But did Cicero for this cauſe write
no philoſophie in Latin? thou will not ſaye ſo, leſt I take the with a
manifeſtlye. What then did Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro? he laborethe in the Latin tongue, as
Ariſtotle before hym did in the Greke, and thou enuious felowe ought to do in
thy mother tongue what ſo euer it be, to witte he amplified his natiue
tongue, thinking no ſhame to borrowe from the Hebru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians and Grecians
ſuche wordes as his mother tongue was indigent of. What, ſhall we thinke
ſhame to borrowe eyther of the Latin or Greke, more then the learned Cicero
did? or finde ſome fitt wordes in our owne tongue able to expreſſe our
meaning as Ariſtotle did? ſhall we I ſaye be more vnkynde to our natiue
tongue and countrey then was thieſe men to theirs? But thou wilt ſaye, our
tongue is bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous, and theirs is eloquent? I aunſwere thee as Anacharſis
did to the Athenienſes, who called his Scithian tongue barbarous, yea
ſayethe he, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charſis is barbarous amongeſt the Athenienſes, and ſo
are the Athenienſes amongeſt the Scythyans, by the which aunſwere he
ſignified that euery mans tongue is eloquent ynoughe for hym ſelf, and that
others in reſpecte of it is had as barbarous.</p>
            <p>Thou ſeeſt (good Reader) what a grounde they haue to defende
their opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and howe they labour only to roote out all good knowledge &amp;
vertue, and pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te mere ignoraunce amongeſt the common people. Now for to
conclude, it ſhalbe thy dutie to receiue this my litle paynes in a good
parte, and to call vpon God that the vſe therof, maye tende to the glorie of
his holy name, and profitte of our bretherne.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="book">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:8364:9"/>
            <head>THE FIRST BOOKE OF DIALE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CTICKE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. I. Of the definition and diuiſions of
Dialecticke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ialecticke otherwiſe called Logicke, is an arte which
teachethe to diſpute well.</p>
               <p>It is diuyded into two par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: Inuention, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or
diſpoſition.</p>
               <p>Inuention is the firſt parte of Dialecticke, whiche teachethe
to inuente argumentes.</p>
               <p>An argumente is that which is naturally bente to proue or
diſproue any thing, ſuche as be ſingle reaſons ſeparatly and by them
ſelues conſidered.</p>
               <p>An argumente is eyther artificial or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out arte.</p>
               <p>Artificiall is that, which of it ſelf declare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and is eyther
firſt, or hathe the beginning from the firſt.</p>
               <p>The firſt is that which hathe the begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning of it ſelf: and
is eyther ſimple or compared. <pb n="18" facs="tcp:8364:10"/> The ſymple is that,
which ſymplie and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutelie is conſidered: and is eyther argea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or
diſagreable.</p>
               <p>Agreable is that, wich agreethe with the thing that it prouethe:
and is agreable ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutly, or after a certaine faſhion.</p>
               <p>Abſolutely, as the cauſe and the effecte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. II. Of the cauſe efficient.</head>
               <p>THe cauſe is that by whoſe force the thing is: and therfore
this firſt place of inuention is the fountayne of all ſciences: for that
matter is knowen perfectly, whoſe cauſe is vnderſtanded: So that not
without good reaſon, the Poet dothe ſaye: 
<q>
                     <l>Happye is the man withouten doubte,</l> 
                     <l>Of thinges who maye the cauſes well fynde
oute.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The cauſe is eyther efficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and materiall, or formal and
fynall.</p>
               <p>The efficient is a cauſe from the which the thing hathe his
being. Of the which althou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghe that there be no tru formes, yet a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te
aboundance we fynde by ſomme certay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne meanes diſtincte.</p>
               <p>And firſt the thing that engendrethe or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendethe is called
the efficient cauſe. As <pb n="19" facs="tcp:8364:10"/> Ouide, in his firſt booke of
the remedie for loue callethe Slouthfullnes the efficient cauſe of loue,
which beyng taken awaye loue ceaſethe: for thus he there ſayethe.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>When curable thou ſhalt appeare therfore,</l> 
                  <l>By my ſcience thy healthe for to attayne.</l> 
                  <l>Geue eare, this is my counſaill euermore,</l> 
                  <l>From ſlouthe and Idlenes thou do abſtaine.</l> 
                  <l>For thieſe to fylthy luſt thy mynde prouokethe</l> 
                  <l>And do maintaine that, which they haue once wrought</l> 
                  <l>Thieſe be the cauſes with foode that noriſhethe,</l> 
                  <l>This euill which now is pleaſante in thy thought.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The father alſo, and the mother which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendrethe, and the
nurſſes which bring vp, ar cauſes efficients. As Dido. in the 4. boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke
of Eneidos beyng ſorely offended with Aenee, and ſekyng a cauſe of his
crueltie, denyethe hym to be Venus or Anchiſes ſonne, and faynethe other
parentes to hym.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>O falſe Aenee thy ſelf why doſt thou fayne,</l> 
                  <l>Of Venus fayre the goddeſ ſonne to be:</l> 
                  <l>Or that Anchiſe which dardam hight by name.</l> 
                  <l>Thy author was by waye of parentie,</l> 
                  <l>For dreadfull Caucaſus did thee begett</l> 
                  <l>On terrible and ragged rockes in filde:</l> 
                  <l>And raging Tygres noryſhes was ſette,</l> 
                  <l>To geue the ſucke of vdder rude and wylde.</l>
               </q>
               <p>So Romulus was buylder of Rome, and after hym, Kynges, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ulls,
Emperours <pb n="20" facs="tcp:8364:11"/> and Tutors were the vpholders of it: which all
are called cauſes efficients.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. III.</head>
               <p>SEcondlie the cauſe efficient is eyther ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarie or ioined
with ſome others, of the which ſome be principall and chief doers, others
helpers &amp; ſeruers to the principall. An example of the cauſe
ſolitarie we haue in the 9. of Eneidos: 
<q>
                     <l>Here, here, am I (o Rutilleus) in me</l> 
                     <l>Your ſwordes bare, thruſt in with pythie hande.</l> 
                     <l>The fraude is myne, I am the cauſe onlie</l> 
                     <l>The impotente nothing durſt take on hande.</l>
                  </q> The
ſolitarie cauſe with others diuerſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the principalls and adiuuantes in
the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which Cicero wrote for Marcus Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellus is diuerſlie
ſhewed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For often tyme (ſayethe the Orator) ſome vſethe to
extenuate martiall vertues by wordes, and pull them awaye from the Captai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
and principall doers, and comunicate them to Souldiers, that they ſhoulde not
be proper to the Gouernour of the warre: And certainly in warre, the fortitude
of the Souldiers, the oportunitie of places, the ayde of the Alies, nauyes, and
prouiſion of victualls helpethe mu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che: and fortune lawfully dothe aſcribe
to her ſelf the greateſt parte, ſo that whatſoeuer is 
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8364:11"/> proſperouſlie done, that almoſt all ſhe estemes
her owne. But of this glorie (o Caeſar) which thou haſt not long agoe
obtained thou haſt no fellowe: for all howe muche ſo euer it be (which
verelie is moſt greate) all I ſaye is thyne, for neither the Centurion, the
Captaine, the bonds of men, nor yet the troupes, maye plucke any thing of this
awaye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee: yea that more is, fortune that mystres of all thinges
offerethe not her ſelf in the ſocietie of this glorie. She ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uethe thee
place, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſethe this glorie who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to be thyne owne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The inſtruments alſo are nombred amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the cauſes
adiuuantes. By this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente the Epicure prouethe that the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de was neuer
made, as Cicero teſtifiethe in his firſt booke of the nature of Godds.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>With what eyes of mynde (ſayethe he) myght your Plato
beholde that compoſition of ſo greate a worke, by the which he makethe the
worlde to be made of God: what labouring: w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat toolles: what barres: what
ſcaffoulds: who were ſeruants of ſo greate a worke?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This vngodlie Epicure knewe not that God was able to make the
worlde without any inſtrumente, or other cauſes eyther materiall or
adiuuante.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:8364:12"/>
               <head>CAP. IIII.</head>
               <p>Thirdlie the cauſe efficient workethe by it ſelf, or by
accidente.</p>
               <p>The efficient by it ſelf is that, which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kethe by his owne
ſtrengthe, ſuche as by nature or counſell do worke. As for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the
naturall workyng of the wyndes is ſett forthe in the firſt booke of the
Eneidos.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Then Eurus roſe with northeaſt raging blaſt,</l> 
                  <l>Vpon the ſea, all toſſing from the grounde.</l> 
                  <l>And Nothus with a cruell noyſe right faſt,</l> 
                  <l>Of whyſtlyng winde did blyſter vp and downe.</l> 
                  <l>And Affricus with ruffling tempeſt ruſht,</l> 
                  <l>Furthe of the Sowthe, the roaring ſea to moue.</l> 
                  <l>So that the ſtormie waues from deape out buſht,</l> 
                  <l>And rayſed was the ſandie bankes aboue.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The confeſſion of Cicero containethe an example of
counſayle, as.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The warre beyng taken vp, yea and almoſt ended (o
Caeſar) by no ſtrengthe of hande, but of myne owne mynde and wyll I come
vnto thieſe warres, which were rayſed againſt thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By accident the cauſe workethe, which by ſome externall
power workethe, as in tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe thinges whiche are done by neceſſitie, or by
fortune.</p>
               <p>By neceſſitie, when the efficient is compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led 
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8364:12"/> to do, Suche a one is the excuſation of the
Pompeyans:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yf I woulde ſeke (ſayethe the Orator) a proper and tru
name of this our ſorowe, the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re appeares a fatall calamitie to be ſuddenly
fallen, which hathe preuented vnawares the myndes of men: So that no man ought
to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell that the counſells of mortall men are ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by the fatall
neceſſitie of the Godds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fortune is a cauſe by accident, when beſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the intente of
the worker, ſome other thing chauncethe: as,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By chaunce (ſayethe Cicero in his</hi> 3. <hi>booke of the
nature of Godds) Iaſon was healed by his ennemie, who with ſtroke of
ſworde opened his rotten impostume, which the Phiſitions coulde not
heale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Amongeſt thieſe ſort of cauſes, ignoraunce or lacke of
forſight is nombred: as, Ouide, in the 2. booke of ſorowfull matters
excuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the hym ſelf and lamentethe that he had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne by chaunce ſome of
Ceſars ſecretes: as, 
<q>
                     <l>Why did I ſee or yet beholde with eye,</l> 
                     <l>What was the cauſe, I did by ſight offende</l> 
                     <l>And vnto me vnwyſe and folyſhe whye,</l> 
                     <l>Was euer the faulte by any maner kende</l> 
                     <l>Althoughe by chaunce that Acteon did ſee,</l> 
                     <l>The nude Diane vpon the hearrie bent.</l> 
                     <l>
                        <pb n="24" facs="tcp:8364:13"/>Yet for al this ſhe did make hym a
praye:</l> 
                     <l>To his owne dogges which hym in peeces rent.</l> 
                     <l>Wherfore I ſee, that happ or negligence,</l> 
                     <l>Amonge the Godds, no mercie hathe at all:</l> 
                     <l>But who ſo dothe by fortune or by chaunce,</l> 
                     <l>Offende the Godds, they ſhall in trouble fall.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Here ryſethe the aſking of pardon, as Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero for
Ligarius.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pardon and forgeue father he hathe erred, he hathe done
amyſſe: he thought not to do ſo: yf euer he ſhall do ſuche a thing
agayne? &amp;c. And a litle after, he ſayethe, I haue erred: I haue done
raſhelie: I repent me of my doyng: I flie to thy clemencie, I aske pardon, I
praye thee that thou wylt forgeue me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ignorance of the cauſe rayſethe the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of fortune.
For when any thing chan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceth beſide the hope &amp; entenſion of the doer,
it is commonlie called fortune. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wyſely it is ſayde of
Iuuenall.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Yf wyſdom preſente be,</l> 
                  <l>There is no God abſente:</l> 
                  <l>But fortune we thee ſett on hie,</l> 
                  <l>And eeke a Goddes vaunte.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. Of the materiall cauſe.</head>
               <p>THe matter is a cauſe of the which the thing hathe his beyng:
as, Ouide in the <pb n="25" facs="tcp:8364:13"/> 2. booke of the Metamorphoſis,
ſettethe forthe the compoſition of the Sonnes how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, by the materiall
cauſe, as golde, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buncle ſtone, yuorie, and ſyluer.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>The pryncelie Pallace of the fyrie Sonne,</l> 
                  <l>Which Pillor hawte, ſurmounted farre the ſkye:</l> 
                  <l>With glyſtering golde, and eke with precious ſtone,</l> 
                  <l>In forme of flame, aſcending vp on hye.</l> 
                  <l>Whoſe toppe aboue was laid in fyne order:</l> 
                  <l>With Iuorie ſmothe in colour whyte to ſee,</l> 
                  <l>The duble doores were made of ſyluer pure:</l> 
                  <l>Caſting their beames vpon the dore entrie.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caeſar in the firſt booke of ciuill warres com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundethe
his ſouldiers to buylde Shippes of ſuche a matter as they had learned
before in Brytayne, To wytte, that they ſhoulde make the keele and bottome of
ſome lyght and lieger matter, and the reſt of the bodie of the Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes
with twigges couered with leather.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>I. Of the formall cauſe.</head>
               <p>THe efficient and materiall cauſe beyng expounded, now
folowethe the formall and fynall.</p>
               <p>The formall cauſe is that by the which the thing hathe his
name and beyng. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euery thing is diſtingued from another by his
forme.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:8364:14"/>The forme alſo is engendred togeather,
with the thing it ſelf: as, a reaſonable ſoule is the forme of man, for
by it Man is man, and is diſtingued from all other thinges. The Geometricall
figures haue their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, ſome beyng triangles, and ſome qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drangles. So
hathe naturall thinges: as the heauen, the earthe, trees, fyſhe and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
others. So that euery thing is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded as the nature of it is, if we
maye attayne to the knowledge therof, as in arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall thinges is more
eaſie to be founde. Ceſar in his 7. booke, ſettethe forthe the forme of
the walles of Fraunce.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The walles of Fraunce are almoſt buylded af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter this
forme: The beames of one peece direct in longitude, euery one being equally
distante from another, are ſett on their two endes in the earthe, hard bounde
within, and couered with a greate countermure. The places betwixt the beames
are ſtuffed vp before with greate ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: Thieſe beyng ſo placed and
ſett togeather, there is added, to ouer aboue the ſame another ranke, ſo
that the ſame ſpace and dista<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes kept, that none of the beames
do touche another, but eche beame being distant from the other by an equall
ſpace, is faſt ioyned togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <pb n="27" facs="tcp:8364:14"/> with ſtones, ſett
in betwixt beame and beame. And ſo conſequentlie, the worke is ioyned
togeather, vntill the height of the wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les be accompliſhed and fylled vp.
And this worke is bothe well fauored, by reaſon of his forme and varietie:
hauing here a beame and there a ranke of ſtones one after another,
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing their rankes in a ſtraight lyne: And alſo it is muche
conuenient for the profitte and the defence of cities. Becauſe bothe the
ſtone dothe kepe it ſalf from daunger of burnyng, and lykewyſe the
ſtuffe and matter from ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hing or beating downe: Which for the moſt
parte beyng made faſt fortie footes inward with continuall rankes of beames,
maye nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be broken throughe, nor beaten a ſundre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On this maner dothe Virgill deſcribe the forme of the
heauen.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>There is with in this long place ſolitare,</l> 
                  <l>An Ile extending out two poyntes right farre.</l> 
                  <l>Makyng a rode, where bankes on euery ſyde,</l> 
                  <l>From the deepe ſea the waters do deuyde.</l> 
                  <l>And turne in maner of a goulf right deepe,</l> 
                  <l>On eyther ſyde be hylls and bankes ſo ſtepe.</l> 
                  <l>Moſt huge and highe eke from the ſea do ryſe,</l> 
                  <l>Two fearefull rocks, which ſeeme to touche the ſkyes.</l> 
                  <l>Vnder whoſe toppes, the waters in their place,</l> 
                  <l>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:8364:15"/>Came without ſturre, dothe ſeeme to
holde their peace.</l> 
                  <l>Faſt by a groue and woode are to be ſene,</l> 
                  <l>With fearfull ſhade, &amp; ſhakyng leaues grene.</l> 
                  <l>Right ouer agaynſt his fronte thou maye perceaue,</l> 
                  <l>On hangyng rocks, a darke den or a caue.</l> 
                  <l>Within the which are ſpringing waters ſwete,</l> 
                  <l>With ſeates of ſtone, a howſe for Nymphes moſt
meete.</l> 
                  <l>Within this hauen, when wearye Shippes do lande,</l> 
                  <l>They haue no neade of cable nor of bande.</l> 
                  <l>Nor croked ancors pytched to make faſt,</l> 
                  <l>For they be ſure from all tempeſtuous blaſt.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>II. Of the finall cauſe.</head>
               <p>THe fynall cauſe is that for the which the thing is made or
done. The ende, of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall thinges is man, and of man God. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo euery arte
hathe the finall cauſe: as, The ende of Grammer is to ſpeake congrouſlie,
Of Rethoricke, eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlie, and of Logicke to diſpute well and orderlie.
Iuno. 1. of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neidos, promyſethe to Aeolus the fayre Nymphe diopeian for
ſolace and procrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of children.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Nymphes I haue of body fayre and bright,</l> 
                  <l>Fowrteen, wherof ſhe that diopeian hight:</l> 
                  <l>Moſt beawtifull, I wyll in wedlocke geue,</l> 
                  <l>To thee Aeole that ſhe with the maye lyue.</l> 
                  <l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:8364:15"/>For thy rewarde the whole courſe of her
age,</l> 
                  <l>Indoting thee with gyfte of parentage.</l>
               </q>
               <p>In the defence of Ligarius, Cicero vrge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the his accuſator
Tubero, with the fynall cauſe of the warres rayſed agaynſt Ceſar, and
ſurely (ſayethe he) he ioyned battell agaynſt Ceſar in armes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What did thy naked ſworde (o Tubero) in the Pharſalike
armie? whoſe ſydes pearced the pointe therof? which was the ſence and
fealing of thy weapons? what mynde, eyes, handes? what feruencie of ſpirite?
what diddeſt thou couett or deſire? what dideſt thou wyſhe?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>III. Of the effect.</head>
               <p>THe effecte is that which ryſethe of the cauſe. And therfore
the mouing of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that are engendred, corrupted, or by any other maner of
waye moued: and the thing alſo that by the mouyng ryſethe is called the
effecte, as for example, Chriſt in the 11. chap. of Math. prouethe hymſelf
by this place, to be the true Meſſias promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: beyng aſked of Iohn
Baptiſts diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Arte thou he that ſhoulde come, or ſhalt we looke
for another? And Ieſus aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering ſayde vnto them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:8364:16"/>
                  <hi>Go and ſhewe Iohn what thinges ye haue
hard and ſene: The blynde receyue their ſight: the halte go: the leapers
are cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed: the deaf heare: the dead are rayſed vp: and the poore receiue
the Goſpell: and bleſſed is he that ſhall not be offended in me,</hi>
the ſayinges and workes of men ar contained vnder this place as the wyſe
mens ſeynges and Platoes and Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotls workes, counſails alſo and
delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations although the neuer take effect.</p>
               <p>Vertue alſo and vyce haue their effecte, as Horace in the
firſt booke of his Epiſtles, ſettethe forthe the effecte of dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes:
as, 
<q>
                     <l>What thing is not throughe dronkennes commytt?</l> 
                     <l>For hyd ſecrets he makethe come to lyght:</l> 
                     <l>Hope moſt vnſure, full ſure is made by it,</l> 
                     <l>And naked men conſtrayned for to fyght.</l> 
                     <l>From penſiue myndes, all care it takethe awaye,</l> 
                     <l>Science and artes full often dothe he teache:</l> 
                     <l>Full cuppes of wyne, at ſome tyme do not they,</l> 
                     <l>Make ignorance be eloquente in ſpeache?</l> 
                     <l>The ſtrengthe of wyne, dothe it not eke make free,</l> 
                     <l>The pore man from all care and heuynes:</l> 
                     <l>Forgetting all his former pouertie,</l> 
                     <l>Vnmyndefull of his dolorous diſtres?</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. IX. Of the ſubiecte.</head>
               <p>NOw folowethe the argumente which dothe agree after a certain
faſhion: as <pb n="31" facs="tcp:8364:16"/> the Subiect and the Adioynt. The Subie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte
is that which hathe any thing adioyned vnto it, as, the ſoule is the
ſubiect of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ignorance, vertue, vyce, becauſe thieſe are added
to the ſoule, beſydes the ſubſtance of the ſame. The bodye is the
ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of healthe, ſickenes, ſtrengthe, infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, beawtie,
deformitie, and ſuche others. A man, is the ſubiect of ryches, pouertie,
honours, infamie, clothes, &amp; of his trayne. A place is the ſpace in the
which the thing placed, is contayned: So the Philoſophers do attribute to
their deuyne ſubſtances (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe voyde of all magnitude) a place: So the
Geomatricians vnto their figures Geometricalles, geue bothe place, &amp; the
dif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ferences of places. The naturall philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers alſo more accurately in
the heauen, ſymple elementes, and compounde thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, dothe acknowledge a
place: Which is nothing els, but the ſubiecte of the thing contayned in it:
as for example.</p>
               <p>The lande of Canaan (a ſubiect) is prayſed in the 12. of
Numeri by the adioyntes or thinges adioyned vnto it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So Moyſes ſent them to ſpye out the lande of Canaan,
and ſayde vnto them: go vp this <pb n="32" facs="tcp:8364:17"/> waye towarde the
ſouthe, and go vp into the mountaynes, and conſidere the lande, what it is,
and the people that dwell therin: whether they be ſtronge or weake, eyther
fewe or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye. Alſo what the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de is that they dwell in, whether it be good
or bad: and what Cities the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re be that they dwell in, whether they dwell in
tentes, or walled townes: And what the lande is, whether it be fatte or leane,
whether there be Trees therin or not, and be of good courage, and bring of the
fruyte of the lande. And after fortye dayes they retorned agayne and toulde
Moyſes, ſaying, we came into the lande whither thou haſt ſente vs, and
ſuerly it flowethe with mylke and honye: and here is of the fruyte of it,
neuer theleſſe the people are ſtronge that dwell in the lande, and the
cities are walled, and exceeding greate: And mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reouer we ſawe the ſonnes
of Anacke there: The Amelekytes dwell in the ſowthe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, and the
Hethites and the Iebuſites, and the Amorites dwell in the mountaynes, and the
Cananites dwell by the ſea, and by the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes of Iordan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here Canaan is the ſubiect: The people of the lande, the
cities, the fruytes, trees, and the goodnes and badnes therof is the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iointes
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8364:17"/> for the which it is eyther prayſed or
diſprayſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. X. Of the adiointes.</head>
               <p>THe adioynt is that which hathe a ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte to the which it is
adioined: as, vertue and vyce are called the adioyntes of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye or
ſoule: and to be ſhorte all thinges that do chaunce to the ſubiecte,
beſyde the eſſence, is called the adioynt: as, tyme, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, eyther
proper: as laughyng to men: barking to dogges: or common: as in the example
folowyng. Cicero in the Oration for Roſſoius Comodus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dothe not his verye head and ouer browe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togeather
ſhauen and ſcraped ſo cleane, ſignifie that he is malicious and
ſauorethe of knane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie? do they not vtter and crye that he is a craftie
foxe? Dothe he not appeare fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe of his head to the ſole of his
feete (if the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion and figure of the body without any ſpeaking or
vttered wordes maye bring a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture) that there is nothing in hym but
cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fte, deceipte, and lying: who therfore hathe his head &amp; ouer browe
alwayes ſcrapen and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, leaſt ſome ſhoulde haue the occaſion
to ſaye <pb n="34" facs="tcp:8364:18"/> that he had an heare of an honeſt man.</hi> So
do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the Martiall in his 2. booke, mocke Zoilus.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Thy heare is redd, thy mowthe is blacke with all,</l> 
                  <l>Thy feete are ſhorte, one eye thou haſt to ſee:</l> 
                  <l>Zoyle, if thou be good, we maye ſaye all,</l> 
                  <l>There is no litle facte comitte by thee.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Clothes alſo, and thinges partaining to our trayne are nombred
amongeſt the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iointes: as, Dido, paſſing to the hunting, is ſett
forthe magnifickly by her adiointes, in the fowerthe booke of Eneidos.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>In the meane tyme while that Aurora bright,</l> 
                  <l>Left the mayne ſea aſcending vp on height:</l> 
                  <l>And Phoebus ryſing brought the lyght of daye,</l> 
                  <l>The choſen luſtye yowthe in beſt arraye</l> 
                  <l>Wente out the ſtretes towarde the porte or gate,</l> 
                  <l>Hauing their nettes with meſhes wyde and greate:</l> 
                  <l>And hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting ſtaues with Iron heads ſharpe &amp; broade</l>

                  <l>The marciall horſemen, next after ruſhing roode:</l> 
                  <l>With Spaniall, dogges, which hunte by perfecte ſent.</l> 
                  <l>Greate multitude alſo were there preſent:</l> 
                  <l>Them which of Carthage greateſt Princes ben,</l> 
                  <l>Abyding all the comyng of the Queene.</l> 
                  <l>Which as yet in chamber did abyde,</l> 
                  <l>Thou ſhouldeſt haue ſene eke ſtanding there
beſyde:</l> 
                  <l>A princelie horſe moſt goodlie to beholde,</l> 
                  <l>Richelie arrayed in purple and fine golde.</l> 
                  <l>Of courage fierce, a beaſt for fight moſt fytte:</l> 
                  <l>With frothing teethe byting his bridle bitte.</l> 
                  <l>And laſt of all the Queene her ſelf comes oute,</l> 
                  <l>Accompanied with ſouldiers in greate route:</l> 
                  <l>With purple cloke beſett aboute with gardes,</l> 
                  <l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:8364:18"/>Hauing a queauer, well furniſhed with
dartes</l> 
                  <l>Behynde vpon her ſhoulders eke did hange,</l> 
                  <l>Her platted hearres like bright golde glyſtering:</l> 
                  <l>Her purple clothes moſt comely to beholde,</l> 
                  <l>Were knite and tyed with claſpes of ſhyning golde.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP, XI. Of differing argumentes.</head>
               <p>THe agreable argumente being expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, now followethe the
diſagreable, w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hich diſſentethe from the matter. The ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments
diſagreable are equallie knowen amonge them ſelues, and diſprouethe
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quallie one another: yet by their diſſention, they do more clearlie
appeare. They be parted into differing argumentes, and gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſettes.</p>
               <p>The differing argumentes be ſuche, as be diſagreable by
ſome faſhion onlie: and are knowen by thieſe notes: not this, but that:
althoughe, not withſtanding: as, Cicero for Pompey.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They did not bring home the victorie, but the ſignes and
tokens of the victorie.</hi> And Oui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de 2. of loue: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes was not
fayre, but he was eloquent.</hi> Alſo Virgill. <hi>Althoughe Priamus was
almoſt dead, yet he did not abstayne:</hi> Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewyſe Terence in Eunuchus:
<hi>Althoughe <pb facs="tcp:8364:19"/> I be moſt worthie of this contumelie, yet thou
arte vmworthy to do it vnto me.</hi> Alſo Cicero for Ligarius, <hi>Calleſt
thou it a myſcheuous acte o Tubero? Why? ſurely as yet it was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by no
man ſo: ſome in deede called it an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, others feare: ſome namyng it
more hard, eyther hope, deſire, hatred or obstinacie, thoſe that call it
moſt hard, name it raſhnes: a myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheuous acte, no man as yet but
thou.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. XII. Of gayneſettes, or oppoſita.</head>
               <p>GAyneſettes are argumentes alwayes diſagreing, ſo that
they maye not be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to one parte of a thing after one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte, and
at one tyme: as, Socrates can not be white and blacke on one parte: father and
ſonne of one: ſycke and whole at one ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: yet he maye be white on a
parte, and blacke on an other, father of one man, and ſonne of another: hole
this daye, and ſycke to morowe: And therfore vpon the affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the
one, followethe the negation of the other. And contrarie wyſe alſo.
Gayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſettes are parted into diſparates and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary argumentes.</p>
               <p>The diſparates are gayneſettes of the w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hich 
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8364:19"/> the one is opponed to many: as, grene, ayſhe colour,
read, are mydde colours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixte white and blacke, of the which euery one is a
diſparate argumente bothe with the extremities, and amonge them ſelues
alſo. So liberalitie, a Man, a tree, a Stone, &amp; other thinges
innumerable, becauſe that one of theſe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be ſayde to be the other:
as, Virgill 1. of Eneidos.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgyn what ſhoulde I call thee, for thy viſage and
voyce declarethe that thou art no mortall woman, Truly thou arte a
Goddeſſ.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. XIII. Of Relatiues.</head>
               <p>COntrarie argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are gayneſettes, of the which the one is
only opponed to the other: and be parted into affirmatiues &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiues.
They are called affirmatiues whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they bothe affirme: as the relatiues &amp;
repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gning argumente. The relatiues are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie affirmatiues, of the which
the one hathe his being of the mutuall ſocietie &amp; affection with the
other, for the which cauſe they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re called Relatiues: as, he is a father:
which hathe a ſonne, &amp; he is a ſonne which hathe a father for by this
mutuall relation they are and ceaſe to be bothe at once. So that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:8364:20"/> knowethe the one perfectlie, knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the the other alſo,
as Martiall agaynſt So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libian.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Thy father when Solibian,</l> 
                  <l>Thy maiſter thou doſt call:</l> 
                  <l>Thy ſelf then doſt thou graunte certaine,</l> 
                  <l>Seruaute to be withall.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Athanaſius prouethe the eternitie of the ſonne of God thus:
as, <hi>It is not poſſible that a father maye be before the ſonne
(meanyng of the relation) But the father hathe ben father from the begynning
(as all men do graunte) er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go the ſonne hathe ben from the begynning.</hi>
And Quintilian in his 5. booke the 10. cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter ſayethe thus, <hi>Yf it be
honeſt to the Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians to ſett out the custome, it is honeſt alſo for
Hermacrion to hyer it</hi> Here (ſett forthe) &amp; (hyer) are relatiues.
After the ſame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Cicero in his booke de Oratore ſaye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the: <hi>Is there
any daunger (ſayethe he) leſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſhoulde thinke it filthy, to teache
others a glorious and excellent arte, the which to learne was moſt
honeſt.</hi> Here (teache) and (learne) are relatiues. Thieſe alſo the
aduocate and clyent: the leſſor and the leſſee: free and bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de: byg
and litle: the hoſte and the gueſt: the huſband and the wyfe, with
ſuche others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:8364:20"/>
               <head>CAP. XIIII. Of repugning argumentes.</head>
               <p>THe repugning argumentes are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie affirmatiues, which
amonge them ſelues do repugne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually: as, Eneid. 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is no healthe in warre, therfore we aſke the
peace.</hi> So hotte and coulde, white and blacke, vertue and vyce, repugnethe.
Likewyſe Cicero in Parad. againſt the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picuria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. <hi>They helde this
opinion ſtowtely &amp; diligently do defende, that pleaſure is felicitie,
whiche appeares to me to be the voyce of bruyte beastes, and not of men, for
thou when God or the mother of all thinges nature, hathe geuen to thee a
ſoule of all thinges moſt excellent and deuine, ſo thou contemptouſly
casteſt awaye and abaſeſt thy ſelf that no difference thou esteameſt
betwixt thee and a bruyte beaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here Cicero opponethe beaſtes and men, as pleaſure is
beaſtes felicitie, therfore it is not mans, So libertie and ſeruitude: as
in Tibullus 2. booke.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Hard ſeruitude I ſee to me prepared</l> 
                  <l>In tyme to come my myſtres for to be:</l> 
                  <l>Fare well therfore thou which haſt me decored,</l> 
                  <l>Fredome and eke paternall libertie.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. X<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. Of denying argumentes.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:8364:21"/>COntrarie negatiues, are when the one
affirmethe and the other denyethe the ſame. And are parted into denying and
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryuing argumentes.</p>
               <p>Denying argumentes are contrarie nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, of the which the
one deniethe euery where: as, Iuſt not iuſt: a beaſt, not a beaſt:
blude not blude: as Cicero in the defence of Murena.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt forgeue nothing, yes ſome thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, not all.
Grace ſhal haue no place, yes when office and dutye requirethe. Be not moued
with mercie, yes in diſſoluing of ſeueritie, yet there is ſome prayſe
of humanitie. I ſtande to my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, yea ſurely, without a better gett
the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo Martiall in his firſt booke, 
<q>
                     <l>We knowe fabella thou art fayre,</l> 
                     <l>A mayde alſo, tru thou, ſo are:</l> 
                     <l>And ryche with all who maye withſtande?</l> 
                     <l>But when thou doſt to muche prepare,</l> 
                     <l>Thy ſelf with prayſes to vp bare:</l> 
                     <l>Then neyther art thou ryche nor fayre,</l> 
                     <l>Nor virgyn I dare take in hande.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Lykewyſe Cicero in the firſt booke of his Tuſculane
queſtions compellethe the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curian by this argumente to graunte that the
dead are in no miſerie: which thing the <pb n="41" facs="tcp:8364:21"/> Epicurian
defendethe. <hi>Now (ſayethe he) I had rather thou ſhouldeſt feare
Cerberus the dogge with thre headdes porter of hell, then that thou
ſhouldeſt ſo vnaduiſedly ſpeake the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe wordes. Atticus. What his
the matter? Marcus. The ſame which thou denyeſt to be, thou admitteſt to
be. Where is the Sharpnes of thy vnderstanding? For when thou ſayeſt that
the dead be in miſerie, that thing which is not thou admitteſt to be.</hi>
And after a long diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, Atticus ſayethe, <hi>Now I grante that they
are in no miſerie which are dead, becauſe that by ſtrengthe of argumente
thou haſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained that thoſe which be not at all, are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe in
miſerie.</hi> This fellowe (ſayethe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in his Eunuch.) ſometime
affirmithe and ſometyme denyethe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. X<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>I. Of depryuing argumentes.</head>
               <p>DEpryuing argumentes are contrarie negatiues: of the which the
one denye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the vpon that ſubiecte only, in the which the other which
affirmethe, is naturally co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. And the affirmatiue is called the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te,
the denying argumente, the priuation. So mouing and quietnes: Sobrrietie and
dronkennes: as Martiall in his 9. booke.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:8364:22"/>
                  <hi>There is no ſober man that woulde do
ſo, Ergo thou art dronke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So to be blynde and to ſee: Ryche and poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: as Martiall in
his 8. booke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yf poore thou be, thou ſhalt alwayes be poore Aemilian,
for nothing is now geuen: but to the ryche.</hi> Of this ſort be lyfe &amp;
deathe: as Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro for Milo. <hi>Sitt you reuengers of this mans deathe,
whoſe lyfe if you thought it mought be restored ye woulde not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To ſpeake alſo and to holde peace: as the firſte for
Catiline: <hi>Why doſt thou wayte for the aucthoritie of the ſpeakers,
whoſe myndes, thou perceiueſt by holding their peace.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. X<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>II. Of equall argumentes.</head>
               <p>COmpared argumentes are thoſe which are compared amongeſt
them ſelues, and are equally knowen, althoughe the one be ſometymes more
manyfeſt and cleare then the other.</p>
               <p>The comparaiſon is eyther in quantitie or qualitie.</p>
               <p>Quantitie is that wherby the thinges com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared are knowen how
muche or how litle they are.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:8364:22"/>And qualitie is eyther of equall or vnequall
thinges.</p>
               <p>They be equall which be of one quantitie. The equall argumente
is, when an equall is declared by an equall: whoſe ſignes and notes be,
equall, alike, the ſame that, aſwell as, aſmuche as, aſmanye as,
neither more nor leſſe: There is a greate aboundance of ſuche
compariſons in the holy Scripture, as the moſt parte of the parables whiche
Chriſt vſethe: as in Mathew. 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Kyngdome of heauen is lyke a graine of muster
ſeade,</hi> Deut. 11. <hi>Alſo I wyll cauſe thy ſeade to multiplie, as
the ſtarres of heauen.</hi> This argumente is diuerſly, vſed by the
Ethnicke authors: as Cicero for Silla:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neither maye I perceyue wherfore thou arte moued agaynſt
me: yf becauſe I defende hym whom thou accuſeſt: why am I not moued with
thee alſo that accuſeſt hym whom I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende: yf thou ſaye I accuſe
myne ennemie: I anſwere a like, I defende my frende.</hi> So the 5. of
Tuſcul. <hi>When as they graunte no lytle ſtrengthe to be in vyce, to lyue
a miſerable lyfe: muſt it not be alſo graunted, the ſame ſtrengthe to
be in vertue to lyue godly? This alſo I praye thee tell me Xenophons wyfe
(ſayethe <pb n="44" facs="tcp:8364:23"/> Aſpaſia) yf thy neigbour had golde more
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious then thou haſt, whether had thou rather haue hers then thyne owne?
hers ſayethe ſhe, and yf ſhe had clothes and the reſt of the
orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of women, of greater estimation then thou haſt, hadeſt thou
rather haue hers? yea ſayethe ſhe: Go to then yf ſhe had a better
huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band? then thou, hadeſt thou rather haue her huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d alſo? here
ſhe was aſhamed to anſwere. Then Aſpaſia began to ſpeake to
Xenophon, I praye the ſayethe ſhe, yf thy neighbour had a better horſe
then thou, whether hadeſt thou rather haue his or thine? his ſayethe he:
and yf he had a better grounde then thyne, hadeſt thou rather haue his? his,
to wytte the beſt: and yf he hadde a better wyffe then thou, haddeſt thou
rather haue his alſo? here Xenophon helde his peace alſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. X<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>III. Of the more.</head>
               <p>THey be vnequall which be of a diuerſe quantitie.</p>
               <p>The vnequall be eyther more or leſſe: That is more, whoſe
quantitie exceedethe: whoſe notes are, not only, but alſo: I had rather
this then that: ſeing this muche more that: <pb n="45" facs="tcp:8364:23"/> as, Eccle.
24. <hi>Beholde that I haue not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured for my ſelf only, but alſo for
all them that ſeke wyſdome.</hi> Pſalm. 84. <hi>I had rather be a dore
keper in the houſe of my God, then to dwell in the Tabernacles of
wyckednes.</hi> Rom. 5. <hi>But God ſettethe out his loue, that he hathe to
vs, ſeing, that while we were yet ſynners, Chriſt dyed for vs: muche more
then now (ſeyng we are iustified in his blode) ſhall we be ſaued from
wrathe thoroughe hym. For yf when we were ennemies we were reconſiled to God
by the deathe of his ſonne: Muche mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ſeing we are reconcilied, we
ſhalbe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued by his lyfe. Not only ſo, but we alſo ioye in God by
the meanes of our Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, by whom we haue receyued
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiliation.</hi> And Cicero for Milo: <hi>Not only he yelded hym ſelf
to the people, but alſo to the Senate neither to the Senat only, but alſo
to the ſtronghe garriſon of ſouldiars: yea not to theſe only, but to
his power &amp; auctoritie to whom the Senate hathe geuen cure of the w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hole
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealthe, of the whole youthe of Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, &amp; of the whole munition of
the people Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine.</hi> Ouide in the remedie for loue, 
<q>
                     <l>Seing the body for to bring out of thrall</l> 
                     <l>Bothe ſworde and fyer gladly thou wylt endure:</l> 
                     <l>
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:8364:24"/>Thy ſoule for to relieue, nothing thou
ought at all,</l> 
                     <l>For to refuſe, ſeyng it is more pure.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. XIX. Of the leſſe.</head>
               <p>THat is ſayde to be leſſe which an other dothe excede by
quantitie: whoſe notes be thieſe: not this only, but not that: this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
that: as Cicero for Catiline. 2. <hi>There was no man not only in Rome, but in
no corner of Italie ouerlayed with debte who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had not aſſociate to the
incredible leage of that miſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous entrepriſe.</hi> Cicero to Philippica
9. <hi>All men whatſoeuer age they be, which in this citie haue the knowledge
of the lawes, yf they were gathered togeather in one place, are not to be
compared with Seruius Sulpitius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. XX. Of the ſimilitude.</head>
               <p>THe compariſon as yet hathe ben in quantitie, now folowethe
the compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in qualitie: By the which we knowe what kynde of one eache
thing is, whether lyke or vnlyke. Theſe are ſayde to be lyke which be of
one qualitie: as Math. 23.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:8364:24"/>
                  <hi>Who be vnto you Scribes and Phariſees,
ye hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, for ye are lyke vnto whytned tumbes which appeare beautifull
outward, but are w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ithin full of dead mens bones, and of all fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynes, ſo
are ye alſo: for outward ye appeare righteous vnto men: but within ye are all
full of hypocriſie and iniquitie.</hi> Gen. 1. <hi>Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more God ſayde,
let vs make man in our owne image according to our lykenes.</hi> Phillip. 2.
<hi>Let the ſame mynde be in you that was euen in Chriſt Ieſu, who being
in the forme of God, thought it no robberie to be equall with God, but he made
hym ſelf of no reputation, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke on hym the forme of a ſeruante, and
was made lyke vnto man, and was founde in his ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parell as a man.</hi> And 1.
Eneid. <hi>Bothe his mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the and ſhoulders were lyke a God.</hi> And Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro
in 9. Philip. <hi>Althoughe Seruius Sulpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius myght leaue no monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te more
cleare, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſonne, which is the very picture and ſhape of his
conditions, vertue, constancie, pietie, and engeyn.</hi> The ſimilitude is
eyther ſeparated or ioyned togeather. The ſimilitude ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated is when
the 4. or ſingle termes are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated and diſtingued: as in Math. 23.
<hi>Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem, which kylleſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, &amp; ſtoneſt
them which are ſente to thee, <pb n="48" facs="tcp:8364:25"/> how often woulde I haue
geathred thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren togeather, as the hen gatherethe her chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens vnder her
wynges, but thou wouldeſt not.</hi> And Virgill in Eglog. 5.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>What thing that ſlepe and reſt on graſſe,</l> 
                  <l>To wearie men appeare:</l> 
                  <l>The ſame to me of thy ſwete verſe</l> 
                  <l>The melodie ſo cleare.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Here, as the hen to her chickens, ſo God is to the
Iſraelites: And as ſlepe to the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſo verſe is to the hearer. And
agayn Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero ad fratrem 1. <hi>As the beſt gouernours of Shippes often tymes
maye not ouercome the ſtrengthe and rage of the tempeſt: So the moſt
wyſe man may not alwayes vanquyſhe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſion and violence of
fortune.</hi> The ioyned ſimilitude is when as the firſt terme hathe it
ſelf to the ſeconde, ſo the ſeconde to the third: as Cicero 3. Ligar.
<hi>Perceiue ye not that the magistrate hathe the power to ouerſee and
preſcribe good and profitable thinges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greing with the lawes, For as the
lawes are aboue the magistrate, ſo the magistrate is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the
people.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. XXI. Of the diſſimilitude,</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:8364:25"/>THey be vnlyke whoſe qualitie be
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe: as 2. Peter 6. <hi>Lord God of Iſraell there is no God lyke
the.</hi> And therfore the ethnicke Antiſtenes vſethe this argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te.
<hi>There is nothing lyke God, therfore God can no wyſe be knowen, by any
image or ſigne made by men.</hi> The author of the booke of Kynges 2. the 18.
chapter. Hauing declared the good qualities, the which Eſekyah was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned
with, ſayethe thus: <hi>He trusted in the Lord God of Iſrael, ſo that
after hym, was none lyke hym amonge all the Kyngs of Iuda, neither was there
any ſuche before hym,</hi> Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero 2. Phillipic. Hathe a greate compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of
diſſimilitudes, ſpeaking of Varro his groundes whiche Antonius had
obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by ſtronge hande. <hi>O miſerable buyldin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges (ſayethe he) by
how vnlyke a maister (but how is he a maister?) were they with holden: Marcus
<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>arro they ſhoulde haue ben for his ſtudies, and not a reſorting place
for filthie lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, what excellent thinges were ſpoken before within that
manner place, what thinges there writen? The lawes of the people Romaine: The
monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of our forbeers, all maner of wyſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and learning: But now ſence
thou haſt dwelled on his groundes (hauing no right therto) all the 
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:8364:26"/> houſe ryngethe with the clamour of dronkar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, the
flore ouerfloweth with wine, the wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les be moyste: children of good
inclinations with thoſe that were ſett for aduantage, and whoores
amongeſt mens wyues were dwelling.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. XXII. Of ofſpringes.</head>
               <p>VVE haue hetherto expounded the firſt argumentes: Now do
followe thoſe which haue their beginni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the firſt, which bearethe them
ſelues to the thinge that they proue or diſproue: as the firſt w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hence
their are driuen. Suche be ofſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: the etimologie, diſtribution, and
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition.</p>
               <p>Ofſpringes are argumentes which do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin alyke, but ende
diuerſly: as iuſt, iuſtice, iuſtly: fredom, free, frely: loue, louer,
loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: good, goodnes, goodly: man, manlynes, manly: as, Iuſtice is flede
out of the Real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, therfore there is no man iuſt whithin the Realme.
Propercius lib. 2.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Sence fredom to no louer dothe remayne,</l> 
                  <l>No man is free, that dothe to loue giue mynde.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Here fredom is the cauſe why thou art free. Cicero 3. booke of
the Nature of godds, when he ſpeake the of Dionyſius the tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te: 
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:8364:26"/> 
                  <hi>Now (ſayethe he) he chargethe that all the golden
tables ſhoulde be taken out of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in the which (after the faſhion
of the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians) it was writen of good godds, ſaying he woulde vſe their
goodnes. The godds are good, therfore their goodnes is to be vſed.</hi> Here
he diſputethe from the effecte to the cauſe alſo, <hi>He is a man, why
maye he not be then manly.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. XXIII. Of the notation or etimologie,</head>
               <p>THe Etimologie is the interpretation of a worde: For wordes are
nothing els but notes of matters ſignified: as Iſaac, was ſo called
becauſe his mother laughed at the promiſe of God made to her. And in the
25-of Geneſis, is ſayed, <hi>After warde came his brother out, and his
hande helde Eſau by the hele, therfore his name was called Iacob: that is to
ſaye: an ouertbrower or deceiuer.</hi> And therfore Eſau being twyſe
deceiued by Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, ſayethe thus in the 27. of Geneſis. <hi>Was he not
iustly called Iacob, for he hathe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued me now two tymes: He toke my byrthe
right: and lo now he hathe taken my bleſſing.</hi> Exod. 2. <hi>And ſhe
called bis name Moyſes, becauſe ſayd ſhe, I drewe hym out of the
water.</hi> 
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:8364:27"/> The Hebrewes vſe to geue their ſonnes and
their daughters names which myght euer put them in remembraunce of ſome
poynte of religion, and knowe when they come to perfection, that they were of
the choſen people. And therfore Nabuchadne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer 1. of Daniell, commaundethe
the chief of the Eunuches to geue other names to Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niell, Anania, Miſaell,
and Azaria, which were choſen to ſtande in te Kynges palace, and teache the
learning and tongue of the Caldeans. The Grecians did vſe the ſame, for
ſome were called Timotheus, that is to ſaye, an honorour of God: ſome
Philotheus which is a louer of God: ſome Demoſthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the ſtrenght of
the people: &amp; therfore (ſome ſaye) that Aeſchines his mortall
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie ſhoulde haue ſayed thus: ſhouldeſt thou be called
Demoſthenes? no not ſo, but rather <hi>Demouorus,</hi> that is a deuowrer
of the people. So do we in the Scottyſhe ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue (to ſturre the youthe to
the imitation of them whoſe name they beare) call ſome Abraham, others
Iſaac or Iacob, and ſome Suſanna after the Hebrewes: And agayne other
ſome Timothie, and Chriſtofor after the Grecians. This argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te is
copiouſly <pb n="53" facs="tcp:8364:27"/> vſed amongeſt the Ethnicke authors: as
Cicero 4. Verr. <hi>O trymme Swyppinges? for to what place dideſt thou euer
come, to the which thou dideſt not bring with thee this daye? To what
houſe, to what citie, yea and ſhortly to what Churche? which thou dideſt
not leaue ſpoiled? cleane ſwipped behynde the? Therfore theſe thy doynges
maye well be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſwyppinges, not ſo muche for thy name (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe thou
be named verres, which may ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifie a ſwypper) as for thy maners &amp;
nature.</hi> Cicero 2. Philip. <hi>Bambalio was father to thy wyfe, a man of no
estimation, and aboue all thinges contempned: who for his ſtutting and
ſtamering of his tongue and dulnes of ſpirite, had this ſurname Bambalio,
for a rebuke and a taunte.</hi> The phiſicions alſo do geue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to their
herbes: to ſome from the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe: as <hi>Hirundinaria,</hi> from the
inuentor: <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipendula,</hi> from the forme: To other ſome, from the
effecte and working: as <hi>Selfwhole,</hi> and ſuche lyke: from the
ſubiecte and place: as <hi>parietaria,</hi> and <hi>ſea trifolie.</hi> From
the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iointe and qualitie: as <hi>ſtyncking marubium deade nettle:</hi> from
the ſimilitude which they haue with other thinges: as <hi>Mouſe eare, fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xe
tayle, dogges to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue:</hi> And ſo forthe from the <pb n="54" facs="tcp:8364:28"/> reſt
of the places of inuention. The vſe then of this place is, to proue or
diſproue, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe or diſprayſe any thing by the Etimolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of it: as
in the former examples, thou mayeſt perceiue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. XXIIII. Of the distribution.</head>
               <p>YEt there remainethe of the argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes which haue their
beginning of others. The diſtribution and definition: bothe the one and the
other dothe reciprocate: in the diſtribution, the whole with the partes: in
the other the definition, and the thing that is defined. Diſtribution is a
diuiſion of the whole into his partes. The whole is that which dothe containe
ſome partes within it. The parte is that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of the whole:
And as the deuiding of the whole into his partes, is called diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution: So
the collecting of the partes to the whole, is called Induction. The
diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution ryſethe of argumentes, whiche do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the agree with the whole,
but amonge them ſelues dothe diſagree. And therfore howe muche the whole
with the partes agreethe, and the partes amonge them ſelues diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greethe: 
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:8364:28"/> ſo muche is the diſtribution the more accurate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. XX<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. Of distribution taken from the cauſe.</head>
               <p>THe firſt ſorte of diſtribution is of thoſe that
agreethe abſolutely, to wytt the cauſe and the effecte. The diſtribution
is taken from the cauſe, when the partes are cauſes of the whole. So
Grammer is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Etimologie and Syntaxe. Retho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, into Elocution and
Action: Diale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticke, into Inuention and Iudgemente. For of theſe partes the
artes do conſiſt: So Virgill deuidethe his Georgickes into fower partes:
as, 
<q>
                     <l>Heare firſt I wyll deſcriue what is the cauſe,</l> 
                     <l>Dothe make the corne ſo pleintifull to ryſe:</l> 
                     <l>Vnder what ſigne and monethe of the ſonne,</l> 
                     <l>Thou ſhalt begyn, to till thy filde and grounde:</l> 
                     <l>Eke at what tyme thou maye vnto the elmes.</l> 
                     <l>Setto the wines, and ſo ſhortlie after this,</l> 
                     <l>What care thou ought to haue of thy oxen,</l> 
                     <l>And of thy cattell the foode and husbanding:</l> 
                     <l>And laſt of all howe greate experience,</l> 
                     <l>The ſparing bees haue into their ſcience.</l>
                  </q> Cicero
for murena. <hi>I vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de (honorable Iudges) that theire was thre partes
of the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, <pb n="56" facs="tcp:8364:29"/> one in rebuking and blaming of his
ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe: an other in contencion and ſtryfe of dignitie The third to conſiſt
in the crimination of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull ſute for offices.</hi> Catullus dothe vſe
this argumnete bothe from the partes to the whole, and from the whole to the
par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: as, 
<q>
                     <l>Fayre Quintia to many dothe appeare</l> 
                     <l>Whyte, long, and ſtreight, ſhe dothe alſo to me:</l> 
                     <l>Yet wyll I not for this ſaye ſhe is fayre,</l> 
                     <l>Seyng in her that there is no bewtie:</l> 
                     <l>Nor yet in to her bodye large and bygge,</l> 
                     <l>A wſhyt of grace or any pleſanutnes.</l> 
                     <l>Fayre Lesbia in bewtie dothe excede,</l> 
                     <l>And from the reſt hathe ſtolen all pleaſant
grace.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. XX<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>I. Of the diſtribution from the effecte.</head>
               <p>THe diſtribution from the effect is when the partes are
effectes, as in the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Cato, wherin he ſhewethe them to haue
erred that ſayde, olde men dyd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. <hi>Thoſe (ſayethe he) that
affirmeth ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitute ouerſeers of the comon wealthe to do
nothing, ſayethe aſmuche as yf they ſhould ſaye the Gouernour of the
ſhippe dothe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, when ſome of the Maryners clymethe the maſt,
others ronne the hatches vp and dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, <pb n="57" facs="tcp:8364:29"/> ſome do make the
pompe emptie the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour in the hynder parte of the ſhippe guyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the the
rudder and ſterne.</hi> Heare the diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution af the generall argumente
into the ſpeciall dothe excell. The generall is the wohole, of one
eſſence with his partes: The ſpeciall or kynde is a parte of the
generall, as <hi>Animal,</hi> a lyuyng thing is the whole, whoſe eſſence
or definition, (to wytt, a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ſubſtance hauing lyfe and ſences)
do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the alyke appartayne to men and beaſtes, which are the ſpecialles
conteyned as par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes vnder the generall <hi>animal.</hi> So is Man the generall
to ſyngle men, and a lyon to ſyngle lyons: and agayne ſyngle men are the
ſpecialles of man, and ſingle lyons, of the lyon. The generall argumente is
ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chief generall or ſubalternall. The ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciall argumente is eyther
ſubalternall or moſt ſpeciall. The chief generall is that which hathe
nothing a boue it more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall: as in our deuiſion ſett furthe in the
fyrſt chapter, the argumente is chief generall of argumentes artificiall, and
of the inartifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall: The moſt ſpeciall which might not be deuided into
other inferiours was the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the forme. The ſubalternall which 
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:8364:30"/> maye be the generall in reſpect of one, and ſpeciall
in reſpecte of another as the cauſe contained vnder the artificiall
argumente, as a ſpeciall, and was generall to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and forme which it
dyd containe vnder it ſelf. The generall and the ſpeciall are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and
ſignes of the cauſes &amp; the effectes. For the generall containethe the
cauſe, w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hich dothe equally appartaine to his ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialles: and agayne the
ſpeciall containethe the effecte of their generall. This is then the reaſon
wherfore the vniuerſall excelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the in dignitie, by reaſon it containethe
the cauſe, as, Ouide in his Metamor. deuide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the the generall, to wytt, A
lyuyng thing into his ſpecialles, as ſtarres (to the which he geuethe a
life, as the Philoſophers do) fowles, beaſtes, fyſhe, and men: as, 
<q>
                     <l>That no kynde, place, or region ſhoulde be,</l> 
                     <l>Of lyuyng thinges lefte voyde or els emptie:</l> 
                     <l>The Godds doe make their habitation,</l> 
                     <l>Amonge the ſtarres, into the highe Region:</l> 
                     <l>The ſcalye fyſhe alſo, by lotte and keuyll,</l> 
                     <l>The flowddes cleare obtained therin to dwell:</l> 
                     <l>The earthe receyued the beaſtes fierce and wylde,</l> 
                     <l>The eaſye ſturred dyre, the flying fowle:</l> 
                     <l>But yet the lyuing thing, which dothe theſe all
excell,</l> 
                     <l>In holynes, and eke more capable:</l> 
                     <l>
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:8364:30"/>Matters deuyne in mynde for to
conceaue,</l> 
                     <l>Was not preſent, the reſt in guyde to haue.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore at laſt was man borne, &amp;c. So, Cicero, in the
firſt booke of his Offices, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidethe vertue, into fower ſpeciall kyndes:
Wyſdome, Iuſtice, Fortitude, &amp; Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce. <hi>All thinges (ſayethe
he) that are honeſt, dothe ryſe of one of thieſe fower partes, eyther it
conſiſtethe in the perfecte knowledge of the truthe and quyckneſſe of
wytt, or in the defending of the Societie &amp; felloweſhipp of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by
geuyng to euery man his right, &amp; fullfilling of thinges promyſed: Or in
the noble courage and ſtrengthe of a valyante and mightie ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te: Or
laſt in obſeruing a good maner and order in all thinges, eyther done: or
ſayed, in the w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hich modeſtie and temperancie conſiſtethe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sometyme we argue or reaſon from the ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerall to the
ſpeciall: as, <hi>All men maye mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie who haue not the gyfte of Chaſtitie,
ergo, Preiſtes and miniſters may marrie.</hi> And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye from the
ſpeciall to the generall in a parte: as, <hi>Abraham was iuſtified by
faythe, therfore man maye be iuſtified by faythe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. XX<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>II. Of the diſtribution from the Subiecte.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:8364:31"/>NOw folowethe the diſtribution of tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe
that after a certen faſhion dothe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree: as of the Subiecte and the
adioynte. The diſtribution is ſaide to be of the ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte, when the
partes are Subiectes: as, The xii Trybes of Iſraell had the Lande of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,
which was a ſubiecte parted amonge them, <hi>vnto the Rubenytes the playne of
Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deba, &amp;c. vnto the Gaddes, Iazer and Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyad, &amp;c. vnto Manaſſes
the Kyngdom of Og, &amp;c. vnto Iuda was geuen the wyldernes of Zin, &amp;c.
vnto Ephraim from Iericho to the wyldernes, &amp;c. vnto Beniamin from Iordan
vp the ſide of Iericho on the northe parte, &amp;c. vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Semeon was geuen
Beerſheba Sheba and Moladah, &amp;c. vnto Zabulon from Sarid ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtward vnto
Chiſloth, &amp;c. vnto Iſſachar Izreelah Cheſulleth, and Shunen,
&amp;c. vnto Aſſur, Nephtali, and Dan, euery one his porcion: as is
deſcribed the 13. 15. 19. 18. and 19. chapiters of Ioſua.</hi> Cieero 5.
Tuſcul. <hi>There be thre ſortes of goodes: Goodes partai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the body:
goodes partaining to the ſoule. &amp; externall goodes. He who dothe attaine
the heauenly goodes partaining to the ſoule, is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be named moſt
bleſſed, then bleſſed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:8364:31"/>
               <head>CAP. XX<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>III. Of the distribution taken from the
adiointe.</head>
               <p>THe diſtribution from the adiointe is: when the partes and
members of the diſtribution are adiointes: as <hi>Of men ſome be whole,
ſome ſicke, ſome ryche, ſome poore.</hi> So Virgill 1. of his
Georgickes, partethe the worlde after the adiointes into fyue partes, whereof
the myddle is parching hotte, the two extremities coulde, and the reſt
temperate.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Circles there by which parte the firmamente,</l> 
                  <l>In nomber fyue, whereof is one ardente,</l> 
                  <l>With the hothe beame of gliſtering ſonne and fyer,</l> 
                  <l>Aboute the wich one other dothe appeare</l> 
                  <l>On euery ſyde with froſen yee congeled</l> 
                  <l>And ſtormes blacke: eke thoſe there dothe deuide</l> 
                  <l>Two other, which dothe holde the mydde region</l> 
                  <l>Graunted to penſiue men for habitation.</l> 
                  <l>By gyft of God.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Caeſar the firſt booke of Frenche warres. <hi>Gallia (now
called Fraunce) is parted into thre partes, wherof the people called Belgi, do
holde one: Aquitani an other parte, and Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, the third parte.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:8364:32"/>
               <head>CAP. XXIX. Of the definition.</head>
               <p>THe definitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is an Oration which dothe clearly declare what
the thing is, The definitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is eyther perfecte and called pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlye
definition, or vnperfecte and called deſcription. The perfecte definition is
a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition which conſiſtethe of the ſole cauſes that accomplyſhed
the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the thing defined. Suche as be the generall argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and
the ſpeciall or forme. So Man is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined a reaſonable lyuyng thing: Here
(by lyuyng thing) which is the generall argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we vnderſtande a corporall
ſubſtance partaker of life and ſence, which is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Man: and
parte of the forme: vnto the which, yf ye wyll put to (reaſonable) yeſhall
comprehende the whole forme of man: So that the perfecte definition is nothing
els but a collection of the cauſes which do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute and parforme the
ſubſtance and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing defined: ſuche as be the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition
of Artes. Grammer an Arte which teachethe to ſpeake well and congruouſlye:
Rethoricke eloquentlye: Dialecticke, an Arte which teachethe to diſpute well:
Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrye, to Meaſure well.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:8364:32"/>
               <head>CAP. XXX. Of the deſcription.</head>
               <p>THe deſcription is a definition which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finethe the thing not
only with the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but with other argumentes alſo: as, <hi>a Man is a
reaſonable thing mortall, and apte to learne:</hi> Here with the cauſe are
ioyned bothe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon and proper adioynte. This compendious and ſhorte
briefnes is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to be fownde in this ſorte of argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, but
deſyrethe ſomtymes to haue a more excellent &amp; magnificall explication:
as Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, is deſcribed by Cicero in his oration for Milo. <hi>yet of all
the rewardes of vertue, if there were a reſpecte to be had of rewardes, I
iudge glorie to be the moſt greate: which only dothe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte the ſhortenes
of this lyfe with the memo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie of the posteritie to come, which dothe make vs
when we be abſente, to be as preſente, and when we be deade dothe make vs
to lyue. And lykewyſe fame is that, by whoſe occaſion and meane, men
ſeame to aſcende and mounte vp to the heauens aboue.</hi> So fame is
deſcribed by Virgill 4. Eneidos.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Anon throughe all the Cities greate,</l> 
                  <l>Of Affricke fame is gone:</l> 
                  <l>The blaſing fame a myſchief ſuche,</l> 
                  <l>As Swifter there is none.</l> 
                  <l>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:8364:33"/>By mouyng more, ſhe breades, and as</l> 
                  <l>She rounes, her might dothe ryſe:</l> 
                  <l>By lowe for feare, ſhe lurkethe fyrſt,</l> 
                  <l>Then ſtraight alofte in Skyees,</l> 
                  <l>With pryde on grounde ſhe goethe, and, perchethe</l> 
                  <l>The clowdes with heade on hight:</l> 
                  <l>Dame earthe her mother brooded furthe</l> 
                  <l>(Men ſaye) that childe in ſpight:</l> 
                  <l>Agaynſt the Godds, when Gyantes fyrſt,</l> 
                  <l>Of Serpentes feeted lyne:</l> 
                  <l>ENCELADVS &amp; CEVS wrought</l> 
                  <l>Hye heauens to vnder myne.</l> 
                  <l>Then for diſdayne, (for on them ſelues</l> 
                  <l>Their owne worke Ioue dyd flyng)</l> 
                  <l>Their Syſter crauled furthe, bothe ſwyfte,</l> 
                  <l>Of feete and wight of wyng</l> 
                  <l>A Monſter gaſtly greate for euery</l> 
                  <l>Plume her Carcas beares:</l> 
                  <l>Lyke nomber leering eyes ſhe hathe,</l> 
                  <l>Lyke nomber harkenyng eares,</l> 
                  <l>Lyke nomber tongues and mouthes ſhe wagges,</l> 
                  <l>A Wondrous thing to ſpeake:</l> 
                  <l>At mydnyght furthe ſhe flyes, and dothe</l> 
                  <l>Vnder ſhade her ſounde ſqueke.</l> 
                  <l>All night ſhe wakes, nor ſlomber ſwete,</l> 
                  <l>Dothe take, nor neuer ſlepes:</l> 
                  <l>By dayes on howſes toppes ſhe ſyttes.</l> 
                  <l>Or gates of Townes ſhe kepes:</l> 
                  <l>On watching toures ſhe clymes, and ſhe</l> 
                  <l>Greate Cities makes agaſt.</l> 
                  <l>Bothe truthe and falſhed forthe ſhe telles</l> 
                  <l>And lyes abrode dothe caſt.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Suche be the deſcriptions of plantes, and <pb n="65" facs="tcp:8364:33"/>
beaſtes in naturall thinges: Of flowdes, mountaines, and townes in
geographicall and hiſtoricall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP, XXXI. Of deuine testimonie, The firſt ſort of the
vnartificiall argumente.</head>
               <p>THe artificiall argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te being expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded followethe
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently the vnarti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall. The argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te vnartificiall or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out arte
is an argumente which prouethe or diſprouethe not of his owne nature, but by
the ſtrengthe which it hathe of ſome ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumente artificiall. And therfore
when the matter is deapelie conſidered, it hathe but a lytle ſtrengthe to
proue or diſproue. In ciuil and temporall affaires, the aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the
diſputer geuethe no litle creditte ther vnto yf he be wyſe, vertuous, and
haue the beneuolence of the auditour: all theſe by one name maye be called a
teſtimonie. The Teſtimonie is parted into a deuine and humaine. Amongeſt
deuine and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall teſtimonies are nombred not only the Oracles of the
godds, but alſo the anſwers of prophetes and deuinours: as Cicero the third
for Catiline. <hi>And to omitte (ſayethe <pb n="66" facs="tcp:8364:34"/> the Orator) the
lightning torches which did appeare by night in the Occident, the veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and
parching heate of the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: as thrawes of lightninges, and fyer breaking out
of the clowdes, earthquakes, and manie other ſuche tempeſtes, which (I
being Conſul) did appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ſo that the godds with a lowde voyce ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
to ſynge thoſe thinges which be now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</hi> And a litle after, he
ſayethe: <hi>At the whiche tyme when out of all Hetruria the Southſayers
being gathered togeather, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that greate ſlaugther and burning did
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche, the destructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lawes, bothe ciuill and domesticall warres,
and the vtter ruine of the whole towne and impire: without the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall godds
by all meanes appeaſed had by their deuine power, chaunged almoſt the very
fatall neceſſitie.</hi> Tibullus.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Yf that in holy Churche the oracles,</l> 
                  <l>Dothe tell the truthe, on my name tell her thus,</l> 
                  <l>Appollo Delius dothe ſure to the promiſe,</l> 
                  <l>An happye mariage: therfore if thou be wyſe,</l> 
                  <l>Kepe well thy ſelf, ſeke not the companie,</l> 
                  <l>Of other men, for that is not godlie.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. XXXII. Of humaine testimonie.</head>
               <p>THe teſtimonie humaine is eyther gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or ſingular.
Generall, as the lawe, <pb n="67" facs="tcp:8364:34"/> and famous ſaynges. There is an
example of the lawe, bothe writen &amp; vnwriten in the oration of Cicero for
Milo: as, <hi>There is a law (honorable Iudges) not writen, but na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally
ſpronge vp, which we haue not lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, read, nor receaued of others, but
taken, receiued and drawen from nature it ſelf, the which to attaine, we are
not taught, but made: not instructed by other, but taught by nature. To witt,
That if our lyfe ſhould fall into an ambuſhe or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpiracie, into the
power and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, eyther of robbers, or of our ennemies, that we ſhoulde by
all honeſt meanes, deliuer our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues from all daunger.</hi> And a litle
after. <hi>Yf the 12. tables woulde a thief taken in the night to be kylled by
any meanes, and a thief taken in the daye (yf he by weapon defended hym ſelf)
to be kylled alſo without dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger: who is he that thinke the Slaughter to be
ponyſhed, howſoeuer it be committed, ſeeing he maye perceiue, that the
very lawes them ſelues: doo offer to vs ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme the ſworde to kyll
men.</hi> Prouerbes are nombred amongeſt famous ſentences: as <hi>lyke
drawethe to lyke.</hi> The ſayinges alſo of wyſewen: as, <hi>Knowe thy
felf. Mediocritie is beſt of all thinges.</hi> There is an exemple of the
ſingular teſtimonie. Cicero 1. ad fratrem. <pb n="68" facs="tcp:8364:35"/> 
                  <hi>And
ſurely that prince of engeine and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Plato, had this opinion that the
common wealthes ſhoulde then be moſt happye and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, when that
eyther learned and wyſe men began to gouerne them, Or that thoſe who had
the care ouer them, ſhould geue them ſelues to wyſdome and
knowledge.</hi> So Chriſte hym ſelf, the Apoſtles, and Euangeliſtes do
con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>firme their doctrine, by the lawe of Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: The Phiſicians, by the
auctoritie of Hippocrates, Dioſcorides, Galen, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che others: the
Philoſophers, by Plato and Ariſtotle: the lawyers, by Iuſtinian: and the
mathematicians, by Euclides. So when there ryſethe any queſtion or
contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie of landes or ſlaughter &amp; ſuche other matters, we vſe
to produce their obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and bynde them whith their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion and
othe, we haue an example of Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, of Cicero, in 5. Phillippicke. <hi>Yea
I ſhall be bolde to bynde my faythe to you (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Iudges) &amp; to the
people Romaine, which yf nothing compelled me I woulde not take in hande but
woulde very muche feare (in a moſt dangerous matter) the fame and
ſuſpicion of raſhenes. I promiſe, I vndertake, I bynde my ſelf
(honorable Iudges) that Caeſar ſhalbe at <pb n="69" facs="tcp:8364:35"/> all tymes
ſuche a Citizen as he is this daye, and ſuche a one as you ought to wyſhe
and deſire hym to be.</hi> We maye comprehende vnder the name of obligations,
gages geuen for the ſuertie of any thing: as, Virgill 3. of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glogs. A
herdman hauing no artificiall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumente to proue that he coulde ſynge
bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then his fellowe, braggethe that he wyll laye downe an heyfer for a
gage. The confeſſion is eyther voluntarie, or forced. Voluntarie, when we
do graunte any thing of our owne wyll. Forced, when by tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes we are
compelled to graunte that which otherwayes we woulde not, and is proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
called a queſtion. Miloes ennemie vſethe ſuche an argumente agaynſt
hym, but it is mocked of Cicero: <hi>Go too I praye you (ſaye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the Cicero)
what was the question, or after what faſhion? hoe, hoe? where is Ruſhio?
where is Caſca? hathe Clodius wrought treaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt Milo? he hath
wrought, then a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Gibbett for hym. He hathe wrought none, then there is
a hope of his libertie.</hi> Hereto alſo maye be referred the ſorte of
argumente which we vſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we do offer to proue our ſayinges by
experience: as Cicero 4. of Verren. <hi>Is there any bodie that would haue 
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:8364:36"/> geuen to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>olcatius (althoughe he comethe of hym ſelf)
the tenthe parte of a denyer? Let hym come now and ſee: there is no man that
wyll receiue hym within his houſe.</hi> Terence in Eunucho. <hi>Examyn in
knowledge and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, in wrastling and fygthing at the bariers I ſhall
geue you one conynglye learned in all thinges, which is decent for a gentleman
to knowe.</hi> And Othe is alſo nombred amongeſt the teſtimonies: as,
Virgill 6. Aeneidos.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>I was thy cauſe of deathe, alas,</l> 
                  <l>Now by the ſtarres I ſwere:</l> 
                  <l>By all the godds, and if there be,</l> 
                  <l>Remayning yet one where</l> 
                  <l>Vnfayned faythe, if truthe on grounde</l> 
                  <l>Or vnder grounde maye be</l> 
                  <l>Agaynſt my wyll (ô Quene) from thy</l> 
                  <l>Dominions did I flye.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:8364:36"/>
            <head>THE SECON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DE BOOKE OF DIALECTICKE CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the
diſpoſition.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. I, Of the definition and deuiſion, of the
diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and propoſition.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E haue intreated in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer booke the firſt parte of
Dialecticke, which is inuen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion: Now followethe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the other
parte, which we did name Iudgement and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. Diſpoſition is a
parte of Dialec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, wich teachethe to diſpone and place orderly the
argumentes inuented, to the ende we maye iudge well and rigthly: for we iudge
of euery thing according to the diſpoſition therof. And therfore this parte
of Logicke is eyther called iudgement or diſpoſition vnder one
ſignification. Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition is parted into the propoſition
(other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called enunciation) or ſylogiſme and methode. Propoſition
is a diſpoſition in <pb n="72" facs="tcp:8364:37"/> the which one argumente is
ſpoken for an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>other. The propoſition hathe two partes, the firſt is
called the antecedent, the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the conſequent: Of the which the
qualities of propoſitions do ryſe. And firſt the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and the
negation. The propoſition affirmatiue, is when the conſequent affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>methe
vpon the antecedent: as, a man is mortall. The propoſition is negatiue, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
the conſequente denyethe vpon the antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: as, Man is not mortall: and
here ryſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the the contradiction of propoſitions, when one conſequente
dothe bothe affirme and denie vpon one antecedent</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. II. Of the true propoſition and falſe, contingent,
neceſſarie, and impoſſible, and of the thre documents of artes.</head>
               <p>THe propoſition is eyther true or falſe. It is tru when the
conſequent is truly ioined with the antecedent, or truly ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from
the ſame: as here it is truly ioined: all man are ſynners: and here truly
ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: no man is iuſt. The propoſition is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led contingent, when
the conſequent be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid of the antecede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſo that ſometyme it 
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:8364:37"/> maye be falſe: as fortune helpethe hardye men, for
granting it to be true to daye, it may be falſe to morowe: So that the
veritie of this ſorte of proſitions is only certain in thinges preſent,
or paſt, and not in thinges to come. The propoſition is neceſſary when
the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequent maye at all times truly be ſayde of the antecedent: as, all
men are mortall. And contrarywyſe, the propoſition impoſſible, is when
the conſequent maye at no tyme be ſayde of the antecedent: as, A man is a
horſe. The neceſſary is eyther of one kynde, or of a diuerſe kynde. The
neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary of one kynde is when the partes are coeſſentiall amonge them
ſelues, as when the generall is ſayde of the ſpeciall: as, A man is a
liuing thing, or the difference of the forme, as, a man is reaſonable, or the
adioincte of his proper ſubiecte, as, A man maye laughe. And this ſorte of
propoſition is ſometyme reciprocate, when the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, not only maye
be ſayde alwaye of the antecedent, and of all thinges contained vnder the
antecedent, but of it ſelf alſo, ſo that the antecedent contrariewyſe
may be ſayde of the conſequent, on the ſame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: as Man is a
reaſonable lyuing thing. <pb n="74" facs="tcp:8364:38"/> nomber is equall or vnequall.
The propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of diuerſe kynde, is when the partes are not
coeſſential: as, A man is blacke or white. And here we haue three generall
documentes to be obſerued in all artes and ſciences. The firſt is that
all the preceptes and rules ſhoulde be generall and of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie true:
and this is called a documente of veritie. The ſeconde that euery arte be
contained within his owne boundes, and withholde nothing appartaining to other
artes, and is named a documente of iuſtice. The third, that euery thing be
taught ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his nature, that is: generall thinges, generally: and
particuler, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly: and this is called a documente of wyſdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. III. Of the ſimple propoſition.</head>
               <p>THe propoſition is eyther ſimple or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde. The ſimple
with the whiche a ſimple ſayng is declared: and therfore it contaynethe a
ſimple conſequent: which yf it do affirme, makethe the whole to affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,
and contrarywyſe, yf it denyethe, the whole denyethe: as, fyer burnethe, fyer
is <pb n="75" facs="tcp:8364:38"/> hotte, fyer is not water. Here, burnethe, hotte, and
water, are the ſimple conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: vpon the affirmation or negation of
the wich dependethe the affirmation or nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole. And this is the
firſt diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of thinges inuented, when the cauſe is ioyned with
the effecte, as in the firſt example. Or the ſubiecte with the adioynte as
in the ſecond: Or the diſagreable with the diſagreable, as in the thyrd.
After the which maner all ſortes of argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes maye be pronounced (except
full compariſons and diſtributions) the agreable by affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng, and the
diſagreable by denying.</p>
               <p>The ſimple propoſition is eyther generall or ſpeciall.
Generall, when it ſpeakethe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally. And here the one parte of the
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction is not alwayes true, &amp; the other falſe. For in thinges
contingent they maye be bothe falſe: as, All man are learned: No man is
learned. And in thinges alſo which be not contingent: as, All lyuyng thinges
are reaſonable. No lyuyng thing is reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. The propoſition is
ſpeciall, when it ſpeakethe ſpecially and of a parte. And here the one
parte of the contradiction is true, and the other falſe. The ſpeciall is
eyther <pb n="76" facs="tcp:8364:39"/> indefinite, or proper: Indefinite when it
ſpeakethe of no certain thing: as, Some man is learned, whoſe generall
contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is, No man is learned. Proper when the conſequent is ſayde
of ſome proper na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: as, Fabella is fayre, whoſe contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is,
fabella is not fayre.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. IIII. Of the propoſition compounde,</head>
               <p>THe propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> compounde is when moe ſayinges then one are
ioyned togeather by ſome coniunction. And therfore vpon the affirmation or
negation of the coniunction, dependethe the affirmation of the whole
propoſition: and here the one parte of the contradiction is true, and the
other is falſe. The compounde propoſition is eyther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregatiue or
ſegregatiue: The propoſition is congregatiue, when the coniunction
ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therethe, and is eyther copulatiue or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexiue. Copulatiue, when the
coniunction is copulatiue, as. Bothe <hi>Eurus and Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> ruſht
forthe. Whoſe negation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction is, not bothe <hi>Eurus and
Africus</hi> ruſht forthe. And here is to be noted, that the veritie of the
propoſition copulatiue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendethe <pb n="77" facs="tcp:8364:39"/> vpon the veritie of
bothe partes: for yf one parte be falſe, the whole is ſaid to be falſe,
as in this example. Bothe man and beaſt are reaſonable, the whole
propoſition is falſe, becauſe the laſt parte is falſe. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to maye
be referred the propoſition contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the relation of qualities, in the
which the relation ſtandethe in place of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction: as.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Suche thing as ſlepe, and reſt on graſſe</l> 
                  <l>To wearye men appeare:</l> 
                  <l>The ſame to me, of thy ſwete verſe</l> 
                  <l>The melodye ſo cleare.</l>
               </q>
               <p>As thoughe he woulde ſaye, Slepe is ſwete to wearye me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
ſo is thy verſe to me. Whoſe negation is, 
<q>
                     <l>Not that which ſlepe, and reſt on graſſe,</l> 
                     <l>To wearye men appeare:</l> 
                     <l>The ſame to me of thy ſwete verſe,</l> 
                     <l>The melodie ſo cleare.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. Of the propoſition connexiue.</head>
               <p>THe propoſition is connexiue, whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction is
connexiue: as, yf thou haue faythe, thou muſt haue charitie: Whoſe
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation is, not althyoughe thou haue faythe, it folowthe that thou muſt
haue charitie. <pb n="78" facs="tcp:8364:40"/> Cicero de fratre. <hi>Neyther yf a
propoſition be true or falſe, by and by it followethe that cauſes are
immutable.</hi> The affirmation ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifiethe that yf the antecedent be, the
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent muſt be alſo. The negation or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction ſignifiethe,
that althoughe the antecedent be, the conſequent muſt not be therfore.
Wherby we muſt vnderſtande, that whenſoeuer this ſorte of propoſition
is true, it muſt be neceſſarye alſo. The ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie is knowen by
the neceſſarye conne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xtion of the partes, and not by the veritie of the
ſame: for bothe the partes maye be fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, and the connexion
neceſſarye, as this: yf a man be an horſe, he hathe fower feete, is a
neceſſary connextion. But if the connextio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be contingent, and only for his
probabilitie ſuppoſed to be, there aryſethe no neceſſarye iudgement,
but only opinion: as, Terence in andria. <hi>Yf thou do that (Pamphile) this is
the laſt daye that euer thou ſhalt ſee me.</hi> The propoſition
containing the relation of tyme is hetherto referred: as, when Iuſtice is
mayntayned, then ſhall peace be in the Realme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>I. Of the propoſition ſegregatiue.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:8364:40"/>THe propoſition ſegregatiue is, whoſe
coniunction dothe ſegregate: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſpeakethe only of
diſagreable argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. It is parted into diſcerning propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and
vnioynyng. The diſcernyng is, whoſe coniunction dothe diſcerne. Cicero in
Tuſc. 5. <hi>Althoughe that by the ſence of the bodye, they be Iudged, yet
they are to be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the ſpirite:</hi> whoſe negation and
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, <hi>Not althoughe that by the ſence of the bodye they be
iudged, they are therfore to be referred to the ſpirite.</hi> This ſorte of
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is true, when bothe the partes is true and diſcerned alſo.
Otherwyſe it is falſe and ridiculous.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>II. Of the propoſition vnioynyng.</head>
               <p>THe propoſition vnioynyng, is a propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition ſegregated,
whoſe coniunction dothe vnioyne: as, eyther it is night or daye: all lyuing
thinges, are eyther man or beaſt: whoſe negations are, It is not eyther
daye or night: all lyuyng thingeh are not eyther man or beaſt: Here the
negatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> declarethe, that the one parte or the other is not true of
neceſſitie. For yf the diſiunction be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely <pb n="80" facs="tcp:8364:41"/>
true, it is alſo neceſſarye, and the partes opponed imediatlie one to
another. Yet althoughe the true diſiunction be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie alſo, it is
not requyred that the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſeparated be neceſſarye: as, This is a
neceſſarie diſionctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: A man is eyther good or not good: and yet this,
(A man is good) is not neceſſarie: Nor this, (a man is not good:) But the
neceſſitie of the diſiunction dependethe vpon the neceſſarie
oppoſition and diſiunction of the partes, &amp; not of their neceſſarie
veritie. The diſiunction is ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes with a condition, as if one ſhoulde
aſke, whether is Cleon, or Socrates come? becauſe it was ſo promyſed
that the one ſhoulde only come. And therfore if the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction be
contingent, it is not abſolutely true, but only opynable, ſuche as
oftenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes we vſe in commen ſpeakyng: as, Ouide in Leanders epiſtle.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Eyther happie courage ſhall ſaue me,</l> 
                  <l>Or deathe of carefull lyfe the ende ſhalle.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>III. Of the Sillogiſme.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Sillogiſme is a diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the which the
queſtion beyng diſponed with the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te <pb n="81" facs="tcp:8364:41"/> is
neceſſarilie infered in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion. For if the propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be
doubtfull, it is made a queſtion: And to proue the queſtion, we take an
argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; diſpone it with the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. The Sillogiſme hathe two
partes: one which goethe before, another that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowethe, &amp; maye be
called, the antecedent and the conſequent. The antecedent which prouethe or
diſprouethe the queſtion, and hathe two partes: the propoſition and
aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, otherwyſe called the Maior and the Minor. The propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
is the firſt parte of the antecede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in the which the whole que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or
the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is diſponed with the argument. The
aſſumption is the <hi>2.</hi> parte of the antecedent, which is aſſumed
vnder the propoſition. The conſequent is the laſt parte of the
Sillogiſme, which con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tainethe the partes of the queſtion, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludethe
the ſame, and therfore it is called the Concluſion: yf any of thoſe
partes be abſent, it is called a mutilet Sillogiſme, or <hi>Entymema</hi>)
if any thing be more then tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe thre partes, it is called a
Proſillogiſme. Sometyme alſo the order is confounded: therfore yf any
doubte ſhall ryſe throughe any of theſe thinges, it is good to putto that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:8364:42"/> to which is abſent, and pull awaye that which aboundeth,
and laſt to put euery thing in his owne place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. IX. Of the firſt forme.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Sillogiſme is eyther ſymple or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde. Symple
when the partes of the queſtion are diſponed with the argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, ſo that
the conſequent be in the propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and the antecedent in the
aſſumption. The Sillogiſme is affirmant, when the propoſition &amp;
aſſumption affirmethe: And negant, when eyther the one or the other is
negant. Generall, when they are bothe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall: Speciall, when there is but
one ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall: Proper, when they are bothe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. The ſymple ſillogiſme
is eyther muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late or whole. Mutilate, when the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is brought in
after on propoſition or on aſſumption: as, 
<list>
                     <item>All men be ſynners</item>
                     <item>Ergo Socrates.</item>
                  </list> And 
<list>
                     <item>Socrates is a man,</item>
                     <item>Ergo hi is a ſynner.</item>
                  </list> The ſymple ſillogiſme is of two ſortes: firſt
the argumentt only goethe before, or fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowethe <pb n="83" facs="tcp:8364:42"/> only. The
firſt ſorte then of this kynde is, when the argument goyng before in the
propoſition ſometyme affirmatiuely and ſomtyme negatiuely, and in the
aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption only affirmatiuely inferethe a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall concluſion: as, in
the examples fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowyng.</p>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Affirmant generall, as.</head>
                  <item>Conſtancie is a vertue:</item>
                  <item>But Conſtancie is Confidence:</item>
                  <item>Therfore ſome Confidence is vertue.</item>
               </list>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Negant generall, as:</head>
                  <item>Folyſhehardines is no vertue:</item>
                  <item>But folyſhehardines is Confidence:</item>
                  <item>Some Confidence therfore is no vertue.</item>
               </list>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Affirmant ſpeciall, as,</head>
                  <item>A wyſeman is to be prayſed:</item>
                  <item>But ſome wyſeman is a poore man:</item>
                  <item>Therfore ſome poore man is to be prayſed.</item>
               </list>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Negant ſpeciall, as:</head>
                  <item>A foole is not alwayes happye:</item>
                  <item>But ſome foole is fortunate:</item>
                  <item>Therfore ſome fortunate is not alwayes happye.</item>
               </list>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Affirmant proper: as,</head>
                  <item>Socrates is a Philoſopher:</item>
                  <item>But Soceates is a man:</item>
                  <item>Therfore ſome man is a Philoſopher.</item>
               </list>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Negant proper, as.</head>
                  <item>Therſites is no Philoſopher:</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:8364:43"/>But Therſites is a man,</item>
                  <item>Some man therfore is no Philoſopher.</item>
               </list>
               <p>But here, in comon ſpeakyng to the ende we maye iudge the more
eaſly, we vſe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pone thus: 
<list type="syllogism">
                     <item>Some Confidence is a vertue, as Conſtancie:</item>
                     <item>Some is not, as, folyſhehardines.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. X. Of the ſecond forme.</head>
               <p>THe ſecond forme is, when the argument being conſequent
affirmatiuely in the propoſition or aſſumption, in the propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
definitelie: the concluſion is brought in lyke to the antecedent: as,</p>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Generall.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <item>The troubled man reaſonethe not well</item>
                  <item>The wyſeman reaſonethe well:</item>
                  <item>The wyſeman therfore is not troubled.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And Cicero in 3. Tuſcul. <hi>As the eye (ſaye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the he) being
troubled, is not able to ſatisfie his office verie well: and the reſt of
the partes, yea the whole bodie being moued out of his good ſtate, is not
able to performe his office: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo the ſpirite being troubled is not well
diſpoſed to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his dewtie well and wyſelie, and the dew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the
ſpirite is, to vſe reaſon: but the wyſe <pb n="85" facs="tcp:8364:43"/> man his
ſpirite is alwayes ſo diſpoſed that it maye moſt perfectlie vſe
reaſon, and therfore he is neuer troubled.</hi>
               </p>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Generall</hi> 2. <hi>as.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>Mortall thinges are compounde,</item>
                  <item>The ſpirite or ſoule is not compounde:</item>
                  <item>The ſoule therfore is not mortall.</item>
               </list>
               <p>As Cicero Tuſcul. 1. prouethe the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie of the ſoule
by this ſillogiſme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the knowledge (ſayeth he) of mans ſoule we maye not
doubt (without we be moſt dull and ignorant in naturall thinges) But there is
nothing admixt with the ſoule, nothing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacte or made of elementes,
nothing compounde or dowble: Which, if it be ſo, ſuerly it maye neither be
put a ſunder nor deuided, nor torne, nor pluckte in peces. For deathe is
nothing els but the departing, ſeparating and deuiſion of thoſe partes,
which before deathe were cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled togeather by ſome copulation.</hi>
               </p>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Speciall</hi> 1. <hi>as.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>The enuyous is not valyante,</item>
                  <item>Maximius is valyante:</item>
                  <item>Maximius therfore is not enuyous.</item>
               </list>
               <p>As Ouide in Elegia 3. dothe conclude, 
<q>
                     <l>Ill wyll and ſpyte full ſlouthfull vices be,</l> 
                     <l>And neuer dothe to gentle manners tende,</l> 
                     <l>And as the lurkyng vyperfull lowly,</l> 
                     <l>
                        <pb n="86" facs="tcp:8364:44"/>Dothe alwaye crepe out throughe the
loweſt ground</l> 
                     <l>But (maxime) thy ſpirite is valyant</l> 
                     <l>And dothe aboue thy lynage reche I winne,</l> 
                     <l>But yet althoughe thy name be greate I grant</l> 
                     <l>It dothe no waye excell thy ſwyfte engeynne</l> 
                     <l>Therfore let others ouerthrowe the innocent,</l> 
                     <l>And let them wyſhe that all men ſhould them feare,</l> 
                     <l>Eke let them beare their dartes aboute the poynte,</l> 
                     <l>Wel dyed with bytyng venym ſhyning cleare:</l> 
                     <l>But (MAXIME) thy howſe and familie,</l> 
                     <l>Is well accuſtomed all proſtrate for to mende,</l> 
                     <l>Amonge the which I praye the haretefully,</l> 
                     <l>To nomber me, and ſo I make an ende.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Speciall.</hi> 2. <hi>as,</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>A daunſer is Ryotous:</item>
                  <item>Murena is not Ryotous:</item>
                  <item>Murena therfore is no daunſer.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Which Cicero for Murena, hathe vnder this forme. <hi>Almoſt no
ſober man without he be madde dothe leape eyther when he is alone, or yet
amonge a moderate and honeſt companie: for immoderate daunſing is the
companion and follower of inordinate ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ketting, pleaſante &amp; delectable
places, and ſhortly of all delytes, and pleaſant pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſies. But thou
captiouſly takeſt that which moſt neadethe be the extreme of all vyce:
and yet vnawares leaueſt thoſe thinges, without the which that vyce is not
to be fown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, <pb n="87" facs="tcp:8364:44"/> for thou ſheweſt no filthy bankettyng,
no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opportunate loue, no feaſting: no loue of bodye: neyther any
extraordinarie expences. And ſeyng thoſe thinges be not to be fownde, what
maye theſe wordes, voluptuouſnes or ſenſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie ſignyfie and thoſe
thinges which be vyces? Beleueſt thou to fynde the vmber and ſhade of
ryotouſnes in that in the which thou caeſt not fynde ryotouſnes it
ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Proper.</hi> 1. <hi>as,</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>Ageſilaus is not paynted of Apelles:</item>
                  <item>Alexander is paynted of Apelles:</item>
                  <item>Alexander therfore is not Ageſilaus.</item>
               </list>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Proper.</hi> 2. <hi>as,</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>Caeſar oppreſſethe his natyue countreye:</item>
                  <item>Tullius oppreſſethe not his natyue countreye:</item>
                  <item>Tullius therfore is not Caeſat.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP, XI. Of the ſeconde kynde of Sillogiſme.</head>
               <p>WE haue hitherto expounded the two ſortes of the firſt kynde
of the ſymple Sillogiſme: Now folowethe the ſeconde. The ſymple
ſillogiſme of the ſecond kynde is, when the argument definitely goyng
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the propoſition, and followyng affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiuely in the
aſſumption, the concluſion is brought in lyke to the antecedent.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:8364:45"/>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Affirmant generall.</head>
                  <item>That which is iuſt, is profitable,</item>
                  <item>But that which is honeſt, is iuſt,</item>
                  <item>Therfore that which is honeſt is profitable:</item>
               </list>
               <p>Which Cicero 2. Offic. concludethe thus. <hi>The Philoſophers
of greateſt aucthoritie, yea very ſharply &amp; honeſtly haue by
cogitation diſtingued theſe thre, which be confuſed. For whatſoeuer is
iuſt, that alſo they eſteme to be profitable: and that which is honeſt,
the ſame to be iuſt: Of the which it is concluded, that whatſoeuer thing
is honeſt, the ſame to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable.</hi>
               </p>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Negant generall.</head>
                  <item>That thing which is voyde of all Counſell, can not be
gouerned by Counſell:</item>
                  <item>But loue is voyde of all Counſell:</item>
                  <item>Loue therfore cannot be gouerned by any Counſell.</item>
               </list>
               <p>As Tere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſayethe in his Eunuche almoſt vnder the ſame
forme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Affirmant ſpeciall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſulls which for their vertue are cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,
ought dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealthe: Cicero is choſen Conſull
for his vertue: Cicero therfore ought diligently to defende the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
wealthe.</hi> So the Orator 2. Agrar. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludethe his owne diligence and care:
<hi>For ſeyng all Conſulls ought to haue a greate care <pb n="89" facs="tcp:8364:45"/>
and diligence in kepyng of the common wealthe: Thoſe ought moſt chieffly
ſo to do, who not from their youthe, but in open place are choſen
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulls. My predeceſſors made no ſuertie to the people Romaine for
me: They beleued my ſelf: It is your dutye to aſke of me that thing which
myne office requyrethe, and to call myne owne ſelf into iudgement. For as
when I ſued for this office, none of my predeceſſors co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended me vnto
yow: Euen ſo yf I offende in any thing, there is no ſhyfte that maye
deliuer me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yow: wherfore, if God prolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge my dayes (althoughe I am the man
who is able to defende the ſame from their miſcheuous &amp; ſubtille
conſpiraties) this I promiſe vnto yow Quirites, that ye haue geuen the
charge of your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealthe vnto a vigilant man, &amp; no fearefull fellowe:
To a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent man, and no Coward or feyntharted.</hi>
               </p>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Negant ſpeciall.</head>
                  <item>He that deceyueth a louyng mayde is not to be
prayſed:</item>
                  <item>Demophon is a deceauer of a louing mayde, as
Phillidis:</item>
                  <item>Demophon therfore is not to be prayſed.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Phillis thus inferethe in Ouide.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>For to deceaue a mayde of tender age,</l> 
                  <l>Which truſtethe in thee, it is no vaſſalage,</l> 
                  <l>Nor craftie gloire: For her ſymplicitie,</l> 
                  <l>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:8364:46"/>Had rather haue the conſtant loue of
thee.</l> 
                  <l>I Phillis bothe a louer and a mayde,</l> 
                  <l>Am by thy wordes (falſe Demophon) deceaued:</l> 
                  <l>God graunte therfore which dwells in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hye,</l> 
                  <l>For thy deceipte, that thou rewarded be.</l>
               </q>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Affirmant proper.</head>
                  <item>Octauius was Caeſars heire:</item>
                  <item>I am Octauius:</item>
                  <item>I am therfore Caeſars heire.</item>
               </list>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Negant proper.</head>
                  <item>Anthonius is not Caeſars ſonne:</item>
                  <item>Thou art Anthonius:</item>
                  <item>Thou art not therfore Caeſars ſonne.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. XII. Of the compounde Sillogiſme.</head>
               <p>AS yet we haue intreated of the ſimple Sillogiſme: Now
followethe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde: The compounde Sillogiſme is, when the whole
queſtion is the one parte of the propoſition affirmant and compounde, and
the argument the other parte. But the argument is ſomtyme conſequent to the
antecedent of the queſtion, and ſomtyme it is the other whole parte of the
propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and than it is only aſſumed in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption. The
compounde ſillogiſme is eyther ioyned or diſioyned. The ſillogiſme
ioyned is a cumpounde ſillogiſme, whoſe <pb n="91" facs="tcp:8364:46"/>
propoſition is ioyned with this coniunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if, and ſuche others, and is
of two ſortes: The firſt affirmethe the antecedent, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludethe the
conſequent, as Cicero conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dethe. 2. Diuinat.</p>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <item>If there be Godds, there is a diuination:</item>
                  <item>But there are Godds:</item>
                  <item>Ergo there is a deuination.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Cicer. 3. offic. <hi>Suerlye yf nature preſcribe that man
ſhoulde wyſhe the commoditie &amp; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of man, whatſoeuer he be
for that he is man, of neceſſitie it is required according to the ſelf
ſame nature, that the vtilitie and profitt of all be comon: Which yf it be
ſo, we are contayned all vnder one lawe of nature: And yf this be alſo,
truly we are forbydden by the lawe of nature, that one ſhoulde miſuſe
another. But the firſt is true, therfore the laſt is true.</hi> Here often
tymes the ſame is not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, but ſome thing greater. 1. Catal.
<hi>Yf thy pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſhoulde feare thee &amp; hate thee, ſo that thou
couldeſt by no meanes appeaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I beleue that thou wouldeſt get thee
ſome waye out of their ſight. Now thy natyue countrey, which is the mother
of vs all, bothe hatethe &amp; fearethe thee, &amp; knowethe that thou
thynkeſt nothing but her deſtruction and ruyne: Shalt thou neither feare
her auctoritie, neither ſhalt <pb n="92" facs="tcp:8364:47"/> thou followe her
Iudgement, neither ſhalt thou be afrayed of her mightie power?</hi> The
ſame ſorte of concluding is, when the propoſition contaynethe a relation
of tyme, as Oenone concludethe her error of folyſhenes. 
<q>
                     <l>When Paris maye withowt Oenone be,</l> 
                     <l>Then Xanthus ſhall run backward vp the vale:</l> 
                     <l>Turne Xanthus, turne, run fluddes backwardly,</l> 
                     <l>For Paris dothe withowt Oenone dwell.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſorte of ioyned Sillogiſme pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lethe awaye the
conſequent, that it may pull awaye the antecedent alſo.</p>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <item>Yf a man were immortall, he woulde be a ſimple
ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance, without compoſition of elementes:</item>
                  <item>But he is neuer without the mixture of elementes.</item>
                  <item>He is neuer therfore immortall.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der the greate aſking one of his wyſe men by what
meanes a man might be God: 
<q>Yf (ſaid the wyſeman) he ſhall do thoſe thinges which
a man is not able to do.</q> Of the which anſwere I make this ſillogiſ. 
<list type="syllogism">
                     <item>Yf a man would be God, he muſt do that which is
impoſſible for man to do:</item>
                     <item>But the conſequent can not be:</item>
                     <item>Nor yet the antecedent therfore.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. XIII. Of the diſioined ſillogiſme.</head>
               <p>THe diſioined ſillogiſme is a compounde ſillogiſme,
whoſe propoſition is diſioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: <pb n="93" facs="tcp:8364:47"/> And is of two
ſortes: The firſt takethe awaye the one, &amp; concludethe the other: as, 
<list type="syllogism">
                     <item>It is eyther night or daye:</item>
                     <item>But it is not daye:</item>
                     <item>It is night therfore.</item>
                  </list> Cicero for Cluentio. <hi>But when this choyſe was
offered to hym that eyther he ſhoulde iustly and godly accuſe, or dye
cruelly and vnworthely: he choſethe rather to accuſe how ſoeuer he might,
then to haue dyed after that ſorte: as he woulde ſaye.</hi>
               </p>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <item>Eather he muſt accuſe or dye:</item>
                  <item>He wyll not dye:</item>
                  <item>He wyll accuſe therfore.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The ſecond ſorte of diſioined ſillogiſme ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kethe one
in the propoſition for the moſt part affirmant, and pullethe awaye the
reſt: as, 
<list type="syllogism">
                     <item>It is eyther night or daye:</item>
                     <item>It is daye:</item>
                     <item>It is not night therfore.</item>
                  </list> And ſometyme the propoſition negant, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this
forme, 
<list type="syllogism">
                     <item>It is not bothe night and daye:</item>
                     <item>But it is daye:</item>
                     <item>It is not night therfore.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. XIIII. Of the methode.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:8364:48"/>THe methode is a diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the
which amonge many propoſitions of one ſorte, and by their diſpoſition
knowen, that thing which is abſolutely moſt cleare is firſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and
ſecondly that which is next: and therfore it contynually procedethe from the
moſt generall to the ſpeciall and ſinguler. By this methode we proceade
from the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent more abſolutely knowen to proue the conſequent, which
is not ſo manifeſtly knowen: &amp; this is the only methode which
Ariſtotle did obſerue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. X<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. Of the illuſtration of the methode by examples
of artes.</head>
               <p>THe chiefe examples of the methode are found in artes and
ſciences: in the which although the rules be all generall, yet they are
diſtinct by there degres: for euery thing as it is more generall is firſt
placed. The moſt generall therefore ſhalbe firſt placed: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> next
ſhall followe theſe which be imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained vnder the general, euery
one orderly vnto the moſt ſpeciall which ſhalbe laſt diſponed. The
definition therefore as moſt generall, ſhalbe firſt placed: next
fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth <pb n="95" facs="tcp:8364:48"/> the diſtribution, which yf it be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold,
and of diuers ſortes ſhalbe firſt diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into his integrall partes,
next into his formes and kindes. And euery part and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſhalbe placed and
deſcribed in the ſame order &amp; place which he had in his diuiſion. It
ſhalbe expedient alſo if the prolixt decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration part them far a ſonder,
to gather them by a ſhort tranſition, for that doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create and refreſh
the auditor. But that the matter may be the more eaſily vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded we
muſt vſe ſome familiar example. If thou wilt aſke (hauing all the
defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones, diuiſiones, and rules of Grammer writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in diuers tables,
&amp; mixt out of all or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) what part of dialectick teachethe thee to
diſpone orderly theſe rules ſo confunded: firſt thou haſt no neede of
the places of inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſeeing they be all ready found out: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haſt
thou neede of the firſt diſpoſition of propoſitions, ſeeing they are
diſponed al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ready: neither of the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d diſpoſition, which is the
iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the ſillogiſme, ſeeing all thinges which might fall into
controuerſie is proued and concluded: only the methode doth remaine. The
Logitian therefore by the lyght of this artificiall methode, ſhall 
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:8364:49"/> take a part out of this confuſed maſſe the
definition (for it is moſt generall) and place it firſt of all: As, Grammer
is an art which teathech to ſpeake well and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gruſly. Then ſhall he
ſeeke out of the ſayd maſſe the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion of grammer, &amp; ſhall
diſpone the ſame in the ſecond place: Grammer is parted into two partes,
Etymologie, and ſyntax. And thereafter he ſhall find out the definition of
Etymologie, to the which he ſhall giue the thirde place. Then he ſhall
ſeeke out the partes of the Etymologie, &amp; firſt the moſt generall as
letters: next ſyllabs &amp; wordes. Hauing the partes, he muſt ſeeke the
for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes: as wordes hauing number, &amp; without number. And laſt he ſhall
knyt and ioyoe togeather with ſhort &amp; apt tranſitiones the end of euery
declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the beginning of the next. And ſo hauing defined, deuided
&amp; knyt to geather the partes of the Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, he ſhall make euery
thing more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt and playne with moſt fitt and ſpeciall examples. And
after the ſame order he ſhall intreate the ſyntax. This is a generall
me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode obſerued in all artes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:8364:49"/>
               <head>CAP. X<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>I. Of the illustration of the methode by examples,
of Poetes, Orators, and Historiographers.</head>
               <p>WE doo not only vſe this methode in the declaration of artes
and ſciences, but in the expounding of all thinges which we woulde plainely
ſett forth. And therefore the poetes, orators &amp; all ſort of writers how
oft ſoeuer they purpoſe to teach there audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, doo alwayes follow this
order of metho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, althoughe they do not euery where inſiſt therein. Virg.
in his Georgicks parted his matter as we haue ſayd into fower partes: &amp;
in the firſt booke he intreateth of common &amp; generall thinges, as of
Aſtrologie, and thinges engendred in the ayer, &amp; of cornes and there
manuring, which is the firſt part of his worke: then he vſeth a litle
tranſition in the beginning of the ſecond booke: 
<q>
                     <l>This much is ſpoke of ſterres and huſbanding:</l> 
                     <l>Now will I thee Bacche begin to ſing.</l>
                  </q> Next he
writeth generally of trees, then ſpecially of vines: the ſecond
tranſlation is put in the thirde part, but more imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and without the
concluſion of the thirde <pb n="98" facs="tcp:8364:50"/> booke, of oxen, hors, ſheepe
and dogges: 
<q>
                     <l>Eke thee great Pales the goddeſ of paſture:</l> 
                     <l>And thee Apollo of ſheepe the gouernour,</l> 
                     <l>At Amphyſus with praiſes I will ſing.</l>
                  </q> And
laſt the third tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the fowrth part is put in the begnining of the
fowrth booke: 
<q>
                     <l>Now by and by with ſonge I will you ſhewe</l> 
                     <l>Thuplandiſh giftes of hony made of dewe.</l>
                  </q> Here
therefore we may ſee that the poet hath ſtudied to place the moſt
generall in the firſt place, and the next generall in the mideſt, and the
moſt ſpeciall laſt of all. So doth Ouide in his faſtes firſt propone
the ſomme of his worke, and ſhortly after parte the ſame: and laſt
hauing declared the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, knytteth them togither with ſhort
tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions: the Orators alſo in there proemes, narrationes,
confirmationes, and perora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones labour to obſerue this order which they
call the methode artificiall &amp; naturall. Here Cicero firſt proponeth the
matter and next parteth it. <hi>Thou haſt bene this fowerten yeares queſtor
(ſayeth he) Cn. Papyrius being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſul: &amp; I accuſe thee of all thinges
which thou haſt done fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that daye to this daye: there ſhall not be one
hower found voyde of thy theft, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious doyng, crueltie, and
miſchief.</hi> Here is <pb n="99" facs="tcp:8364:50"/> the ſomme: now follweth the
generall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition. <hi>All the yeares (ſayeth he) are ſpent eyther in the
office of the queſture: in the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſade made in Aſia: in the office
of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture pertaining to the towne: or in the office of the preture,
amonge the Siciliens. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore into theſe fower partes my whole
accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhalbe parted.</hi> Of the which fower par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and the leaſt
member of euery part he intreateth afterwarde, euery on in his owne order and
place. And in the thirde oration knytteth togeather the firſt three partes
with tranſitiones. <hi>Now (ſayeth he) ſeeyng I haue ſhewne his office
of queſture &amp; firſt digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to be full of theft &amp; miſhieuous
doing, I pray you geue eare to the reſt.</hi> Then after he had ſhewne the
faultes of the Ambaſſade, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the tranſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the office of the
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>But now let vs come (ſayeth he) to that worthie preturie and to
thoſe faultes, which be more manifeſt to thoſe that be here preſent,
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to me although I haue ſtudied &amp; prepared my ſelfe to declare the
ſame.</hi> This tranſition is more imperfect lacking an epiloge. And laſt
in the begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning of the fowerth oratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he maketh ſuch a tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſition to the
fowerth, part which is of the preturie amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Sicilie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. 
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:8364:51"/> 
                  <hi>There is many thinges (honorable Iudges) which of
neceſſitie I moſt pretermit, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de I maye ſpeake a litle of theſe
thinges committed to my charge. For I haue taken vppon me the cauſe of
Sicilia, that charge hath pulled me to this buſines.</hi> So Liuius in the
beginning comprehendeth the ſome of ſeuentie yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and therafter
deuideth the ſame by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cades.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. X<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>II. Of the craftie and ſecrete methode.</head>
               <p>THis methode then in dyuers enuntia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of one kynde, being
knowen eather by there owne diſpoſition, or the diſpoſition of the
ſillogiſme ſhalbe obſerued how often ſoeuer the matter is clearly to
be vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded: But when with delectation or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther motion thy chief
purpoſe is to deceaue the auditor, then thou ſhall put ſome thing away
which doth appartaine to thy matter, as definitions, diuiſions and
tranſitions: &amp; ſet in there places thinges appartaining nothing to the
matter: as digreſſiones from the purpoſe, &amp; long tarying vpon the
mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: but moſt chiefly ſee that in the begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning thou inuerte thy order,
and place ſome ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedentes <pb n="101" facs="tcp:8364:51"/> after there
conſequentes. And ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely this more imperfect forme of methode in reſpect
of the exact rule obſerued in the other, is not only mutilate by reaſon of
the taking away of ſome of the matter: and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doundeth by the eking to of
thinges extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie: but hauing ſome degrees of the order inuerted, is
prepoſterous and out of all good faſhion and order.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>FAVLTES ESCAPED.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Page 8 line 2 Reade argument or.</item>
               <item>pag. 17 lin. 21 declareth.</item>
               <item>pag. 24 lin. 11 agayne vvithout in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogation.</item>
               <item>pag. 30 lin. 21 ignoranter.</item>
               <item>pag. 45 lin. 26 Seing the, &amp;c. his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ought to be
put to the next Chap. 19.</item>
               <item>pag. 49 lin. 20 Marcus Varro vvoulde thei.</item>
               <item>pag. 72 lin. 1 of</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
